<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The arte of Christian saylinge. Or a comfortable treatis written on these words of the prophet Dauid in the 55. Psal. 22. 23. verses</title>
            <author>Hull, John, 1569 or 70-1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13929</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851786</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851786</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1312:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The arte of Christian saylinge. Or a comfortable treatis written on these words of the prophet Dauid in the 55. Psal. 22. 23. verses</title>
                  <author>Hull, John, 1569 or 70-1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 56 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Harrison 3 and S. Stafford] for Iohn Harison [4] dwelling in pater noster row at the signe of the gilden Vnicorne and Bible and are there to be sould,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J. Harrison 3 printed only the preliminaries--STC.</note>
                  <note>Printers names and publisher's exact designation from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The arte of Christian sayling.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; some pages stained and some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalm LV --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17077:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ARTE OF CHRISTIAN SAYLINGE. OR A comfortable treatis written on theſe words of the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the 55. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.
23. <hi>verſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Caſt thy burthen vpon the Lord and he ſhall nouriſh thee, he will not ſuffer the righteous, to fall for euer, and thou O God ſhalt throw them downe into the pit of corruption.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Hariſon</hi> dwelling in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoſter row at the ſigne of the gilden Vnicorne and Bible and are there to be ſould. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17077:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17077:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull Maiſter <hi>Oliuer Cromwell</hi> Eſquire health honor and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Poets hane prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated of an age, which they epithite,
<hi>marmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, durum:</hi> ſteely, ſtonie, harde, and roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie.
<note place="margin">Math. 24. Tim. 2.3.</note> The ſcriptures haue prophicied of a time, wher in Charitie, ſhould wax cold, men ſhould be couetous, and louers of themſelues. And experience hath proued theſe to be the dayes of vſurie, <hi>Simonie,</hi> deceit, oppre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion, theft, and want of charitie, yet
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was full of hoſpitalitie:
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Lot</hi> receiued ſtrangers: <hi>Cleomenes</hi> and
<hi>Polomaeus</hi> had the ſurnames, of benefactors.
<note place="margin">Alex. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The Barbarians had pittie on the ſeabeaten trauilers.
<note place="margin">Alex. 1.</note> And Iob would not let the ſtranger lodge in the ſtreete, but ſette open his doores to him, that wente by the way.
<note place="margin">Acts. 28.</note> Yea ſaith he, if I reſtrained the poore of their deſire, cauſed the eyes of the widdow to faile, eate my morſels alone, and not fede the fatherleſſe.
<note place="margin">Iob. 31.</note> If I with held the hirelings wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, got goods by oppreſſion, or let the naked periſh for want of clothing. then let thiſtles grow in ſtead of wheate, cockle inſtead of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, my arme fall from my ſhoulder, and bee<pb facs="tcp:17077:3"/>broken from the bone. But the Mimicke could tell, that <hi>bona comparat praeſidia miſerecor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> the mercifull ſhall finde mercie.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 58.</note> The libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſhall haue plentie, and the waterer raine <hi>Martianus</hi> ſaid that true riches were
<hi>ſua indigen tibus largiri,</hi> to feede the hungry, lodge the wanderer. and cloth the naked.
<note place="margin">Oze. 6.</note> God deſired, Chriſt bleſſed, and the Saints practiſed, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.
<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.
5.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn's</hi> ſermons were all for loue: <hi>Peters</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations for hoſpitalitie: <hi>Timothes</hi> charge for good workes:
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 44.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> cowncels for pittie: &amp; <hi>Paules</hi> exhortations for loue and charitie.
<note place="margin">Ier. com. in</note> Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (right worſhipful) this ſmall treatis of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſayling preſt forth to try the ſurges of cenſuring ſeas,
<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> hath preſumed vpon your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage (the true ſupporter of pouertie) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect it againſt the prating aſſalts of the peuiſh pirat.
<note place="margin">Peter 1.4.</note> Being imboldened therunto by your loue to learning, hoſpicality to ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers,
<note place="margin">Tim. 1.6.</note> benefice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to neighbors, piety to kindred, pitty to the pore &amp; bounty vnto al,
<note place="margin">Dentron. 10 Rom. 1.2. Co. 3.</note> whoſe beginnings it bleſſeth whoſe proceedings it praiſeth, &amp; whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance it confirmeth vnto the day of your arriuall in the heauenly hauen of eternall happineſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips to commande IOHN HVLL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17077:3"/>
            <head>The preface vnto the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An in this life may not vnfuly bee reſembled vnto a ſhippe vpon the ſea, for her ſwiftnes in ſayling: facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in breaking: eaſineſſe in hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſimilitude in bearing: hazard in loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; and ioy in arriuing.
<note place="margin">Cor. 9.24.</note> For it paſſeth ſwiftly, compared to a race called ſtadium
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Lucian in Caronte.</note> becauſe it laſted but the holding of Hercules. To a bubble
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> becauſe as ſome bubbles no ſooner riſe but fall, others ſtay a little longer, ſo doth man. To a miſt: to a clowde: to a poſt, for <hi>nil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud eſt preſetis vitoe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus, quem cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ad morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca. Epiſt. 59.</note> the time of this life is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but a continuall poſting vnto death <hi>tunc cu creſcimus, vita decreſdit,</hi> euen then, when our bodies are increaſing, our life is decreaſing: not vnlike Ionas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard
<pb facs="tcp:17077:4"/>quickely cume and quickely gone. Thee-phraſtus complained oſ the breuitie of mans life. The Indians could not ſhew an olde man Quintilian made it but a day, the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt but a watch in the night. Pindarus but a dreame. Sophocles but a breath De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius but the very pricke of time, let vs then remember our ſelues and conſider, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit puncto minus hoſtis, quam ſit malus antiquius, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſae voluptates.</hi> How this life is moſt ſhort, the Diuell moſt cruell, pleaſure moſt vaine, honour moſt deceit full, and riches moſt peſtilent: but for thoſe that ſaile for heauen the promiſes, are moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable performances, moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, and all good without compaire, whoſe King is diuinitie, whoſe law is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and whoſe end is eternitis.
<note place="margin">Acts. 5.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs haſt vnto our hauen. Secondly it is brittell, and ſoone broken:
<note place="margin">Varanius.</note> like flame ſoone kindled, like a ſparke ſoone quencht and like a reede ſoone brooſed.
<note place="margin">Val. Max. lib. 9.12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> died ſuddenly being rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. <hi>Galcion</hi> while he was barbing.
<hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon</hi> while he was laughing.
<note place="margin">Plin. 7.53.</note> 
               <hi>Sophocles</hi> ioying.
<hi>Hely</hi> ſorrowing. <hi>Domitius</hi> after eating, <hi>Anacreo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> drinking.
<note place="margin">Laertius.</note> 
               <hi>Cleanthes</hi> faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb facs="tcp:17077:4"/>
               <hi>Attila</hi> bleeding: <hi>Perſeus</hi> watching and
<hi>Bithon</hi> ſleeping. Verely the earth beares not any thing more fraile then fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le man, not a miſſe compared vnto a ſhip, <hi>qui dum proſpero vento, velis plenis pla cido maricurſum peragit, ſaepe inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rato ac repente frangitur:</hi> that while the winde blowes fairly, and ſhe ſayles me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily is ouertaken by miſchance and broken ſuddenly. Let vs therefore be alwayſe in a reddines: it is Chriſts commandement the Poets cownſell: &amp; reaſons rule, watch ſaith Chriſt:
<note place="margin">Math. 27.</note> 
               <hi>viue memor mortis</hi> ſaith the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et liue mindfull of death: for ſaith rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
<note place="margin">Make. 25.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Fata mane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes expectat auarus,</l>
               <l>portitor vt turbae vix ſatis vna ratis mus<note place="margin">Perſiuis.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Tendimus huc o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, meta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propera ad vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </l>
               <l>omnia ſub legesmors vocat atra ſuas<note place="margin">Chilo.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vid ad liuium.</note> All men muſt dye were they as ſtrong as Sampſon, rich as Diues, faire as <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> wiſe as <hi>Salomon,</hi> zelus as <hi>Elias,</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as <hi>Dauid</hi> and old as <hi>Adam.</hi> But when, where, or how, to day or to morrow, by ſea or by land, by fire or by ſworde, who can tell?</p>
            <q>
               <l>Mille modis lethi miſeros mors vna fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:17077:5"/> Death hath a thowſand wayes to ſeaze vpon. By ſudden death as vpon <hi>Pindarus:</hi> by poyſon as vpon
<hi>Socrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 10.</note>by ſtrang fire as vpon
<hi>Hadab</hi> and <hi>Abing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> by water as vpon
<hi>Pharoh</hi> and his hoſt, by earth as vpon <hi>Chorah</hi> and his company.
<note place="margin">Numb. 17.</note> By the halter as
<hi>Achitophell,</hi> by the ſworde as <hi>Saule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 2.17.</note> and therefore let vs bee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 1.31.</note> Thirdly as the ſhippe is hindered by contrarie windes, ouermuch loading, and vnskilfull ayming from arriuing at the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed hauen: ſo is man by vaine pride, inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate loue, fooliſh feare: heauy ſin: blinde ignorance, and an vnbeleeuing heart ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from attaining his deſired hauen. For pride and vaine glory blew the Angells from heauen, made ſhipwracke of <hi>Adam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 12.</note> ouerthrowed <hi>Herod:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.</note> and threw
<hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadonaſar</hi> from the ſterne.
<note place="margin">Gen. 11.</note> It confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Babell:
<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> condemned Capernaum,
<note place="margin">Mark. 9.33</note> and made Senacharib an example, for all that behold him to be godly.
<note place="margin">Theſſ. 2. 4.</note> It infected Chriſts diſciples: it diſtroyed <hi>Corach: Aman: Abſolon, Adoniah.</hi> It is the marke of Antichriſt and it hindered the ſcribes and Phariſes from heauen becauſe they loued<pb facs="tcp:17077:5"/>the prayſe of men more then the prayſe of God.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 12.43.</note> It vniuſtified the Phariſies: deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth falſe Apoſtles: and vnmasketh Hyppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note> It is like a rocke that will breake our ſhip: a winde, that blaſteth our fruite: and a thiefe, that will ſteale our goods, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by <hi>Seneca</hi> to a whirlewind: by
<hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> to a bladder: and by <hi>Auſtine</hi> to ſmoake.
<note place="margin">Cor. 2.10:</note> The ſcripture ſaith, there glory, is there ſhame, yea that of all thinges it is moſt miſerable. For
<hi>ſequitur ſuperbos Victor a tergo deus:</hi> God reſiſteth the proud, conquers the hauty: and will one day bring there ſtinking bodies,
<hi>magno faetore</hi> from there naſtie ſepulchers.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.</note> Let not therefore the wiſe man glorie in his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: the ſtrong man in his ſtrength, nor the rich man in his riches.
<note place="margin">Ier. 17</note> But let him that glorieth glory in the Lord, before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e <hi>Dauid</hi> would not be examined.<note place="margin">Iob. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> was caſt downe, <hi>Elias</hi> hid his face, and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> called, himſelfe duſt and aſhes, yea man is vanity: the heart wicked. and the heauens vncleane: ſtrike therefore ſaile, leaſt this winde do catch thee,</p>
            <p>The ſecond contrary winde is iuordinat loue of riches, pleaſure kindred, and friends<pb facs="tcp:17077:6"/>The firſt hindred the bidden gueſts ſloed <hi>Achan,</hi> killed <hi>Ahab,</hi> And hanged
<hi>Iudas:</hi> it is birdlime, a net, and ſtrong wine, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe is compared to a thirſty dropſie: vgle monſter, rauening harpy, drowning fire and a violent floud, called by the Poets the mother of miſchefe, the head of all euill <hi>mater ſcelerum</hi> and what not?
<note place="margin">Phoſilid.</note> By the Philoſopher:
<hi>elementum malorum,</hi> the cheife citty of ſin, the element of euill.
<note place="margin">Apollod.</note> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are compared to a runnagate ſeruant to an Egle,
<note place="margin">Cland. 2.</note> to nothing <hi>Fortuna vitrea eſt dumſplendet frangitur fortune</hi> for time is like glaſſe beautifull but brickle.
<note place="margin">Timon.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The marchant bragging of his wealth is puffed vp: when as oftentimes the wind will make claime vnto his good, and be lord of his trafique,
<note place="margin">Antipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> Set not therefore thy hart vpon riches, loue not the world, and beware of couetouſneſſe, for the couetous man is like fire, the graue, an hell that neuer haue enough, like the wolfe, the hogge, and the dog. that following two men leaues the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, and cleaues vnto his maſter: ſo the worldling for ſakes Chriſt and follows mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, as <hi>Gehezi,</hi> that to gette the mony loſt his maſter: and what ſhall it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitte<pb facs="tcp:17077:6"/>thee to win the world and looſe thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>The ſecond hindred <hi>Eſay: Diues,</hi> the Epicure.
<note place="margin">Sam. 2.11.</note> It led <hi>Dauid</hi> to wantonneſſe, <hi>Salomon</hi> to idolatry, <hi>Sampſon</hi> to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:
<note place="margin">Kings. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> to cruelty, Not to recken vp <hi>Sardanapalus: Antonie: Mecenas: Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula: Nero:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudge. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> it hindred <hi>Vliſſes</hi> companions from ſayling towards there country.
<note place="margin">Marke. 9.</note> It is <hi>Heſiodes Pando<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra,</hi> the Diuels baite, and the ſoules enemy <hi>Inde adſpice late florentes quondam luxus quas verteret vrbes: quippe nec ira deum tantum, nec tela, nec hoſtes: quantum ſola noces animis illapſa vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Silius. 15.</note> It changed Rome: burned ſodom: vanquiſhed Babilon, and deſtroyed Iſraell It turnes men into beaſts, women into ſwine and makes all worſe, <hi>aſino vel cane,</hi> then the dog, or the aſſe.</p>
            <p>The third hindred the Pagan from bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme the Papiſt from verity:
<note place="margin">Chriſtos.</note> 
               <hi>Ely</hi> from pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie It is <hi>aries quo murus Euangilij qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom. 5.18.</note> the Ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me that ſhakes the walles of the Goſpell.
<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Heliad.</note> Theſe are our goods, our trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, our ſelues. <hi>Ionathan</hi> will hazard him elfe for
<hi>Dauid, Hercules</hi> goe to hell for<pb facs="tcp:17077:7"/>
               <hi>Theſeus: Damon</hi> dye for <hi>Pithias</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong the Egyptians, there was a kind of frendſhip of thoſe that would die together, yet our christian viage muſt breake al <hi>licet parvulusex collo pendeat nepos, licet ſparfo crine et ſciſſis veſtibus vbera, qui bus te nutriat, mater oſtendat, licet in limine pater iaceat: percultatum perge patrem, ſiccis oculis ad vexillum cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis euola.</hi> Neither father nor mother. ſon nor daugher, kinſman nor frende muſt keepe vs from Chriſt. <hi>Abraham</hi> will looſe
<hi>Iſaac</hi> for God.
<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note>
               <note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> The mother the ſeuen childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Machabes, the diſciples leaue all for Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Acts. 21.</note> and <hi>Paule</hi> will die for the name of Ieſus. But <hi>Tamerus</hi> for bis bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers loue will chang his religion, <hi>Iulians</hi> treaſurer for his maſters ſake abandon his profeſſion, ye <hi>Pilate</hi> for the loue of men will condemne euen Chriſt himſelfe. Howbeit it ſhall not alwaiſe refl vnpuniſhed.
<hi>Hely</hi> broke his necke: <hi>Pilate</hi> killed himſelfe,
<hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morus</hi> was his owne hangman, and <hi>Iulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> Treaſurer died ſuddenly vomiting out his bloud, Yet all this is nothing to that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full repulſe Chriſt ſhall giue them at hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen gates, ſaying, I know you not, for hee<pb facs="tcp:17077:7"/>that denies him before men, his will Chriſt deny before his Father that is in heauen.</p>
            <p>The third contrary winde is feare of pouertie: perſecutions: puniſhments: reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: rayling: ſcorning: whipping: Impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: baniſhing: killing, all which are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to chriſtian ſaylers.
<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> For the Church is <hi>Noe</hi> and it muſt be toſſed her <hi>poeſie facere bonum et habere malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to doe well but to haue ill, and her coulor ſhall be blacke, and cannot be changed. A god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans life is no life but calamity, <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> dayes were few and euill.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was toſſed from poſt to piller: the ſaints ſuffered all kind of miſery: yea Chirſt himſelfelfe,
<note place="margin">Greg.</note> 
               <hi>non exiit ſine flagello, qui ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit ſine peccato,</hi> he muſt not depart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whipping, that came and liued without ſinning. This hindred many from ſayling after Christ, as
<hi>Ciprian</hi> reporteth. The Theater relateth, and the Tripartite recor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth, Iewes, and Gentles, Grecians, and Bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>barians. <hi>Liberius Spiera,</hi> Nichomachus This made <hi>Aaron</hi> to make the Idolatrous calfe.
<hi>Nichodemus</hi> to come by night vnto Chriſt, <hi>Peter</hi> to denie his maſter, Origen to<pb facs="tcp:17077:8"/>offer to an Idol, and <hi>Damaſcet</hi> to worſhip <hi>Mahomet,</hi> howbeit Chriſt muſt enter by the croſſe into glorie, his followers by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions in to heauen, and they which endeuour ſhalbe bleſſed and receiue the croune of life.</p>
            <p>The ſecond hinderer is the greatneſſe of the Lord: and of all the burdens that euer man did beare, ſin is the heauieſt, like a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone about our necks, a maſſe of lead about our feete, a rocke of ſtone vpon our heads, and a mightie mountaine on our backes.
<note place="margin">Decleſ. 22</note> So heauy as heauen could not hold it: Paradiſe not beare it: nor earth ſuſtaine it, but hell muſt receiue <hi>Corath, Dathan</hi> &amp; <hi>Abiram.</hi> The ſinner is like a filthy ſtone, that cannot rowle, a blindfold mowle, that cannot ſee and a loaden aſſe, that cannot goe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt needes be hindered.
<note place="margin">Sam. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> Purge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this filth, caſt away this vaile, and diſburde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſhippe. The auncient gameſters would wreſtle naked:
<hi>Dauid</hi> would not fight in <hi>Saules</hi> harneſſ: and hee; that vſeth maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, abſtaineth from all thinges, that may hinder him.
<note place="margin">Cor. 1.9.25.</note> Behold Chriſt came to beare thy burden, vnload thy veſſell, and eaſe thy ſhippe, He was made the ſon of man, that<pb facs="tcp:17077:8"/>thou mightſt be the child of God, he was lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſwadling bands, that thou mightſt be looſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bonds of ſin. He was wrapped in ragged clowts, that that thou mightſt be cloathed with his righteouſneſſe innocency He was poore that thou mightſt he rich: A ſtranger that thou mighſt be ſure of an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly citie. Hee payed tribute that thou mighſt he free from the trihute of hell. Hee was debaſed, that thou mightſt be exalted, accurſed, that thou mightſt be iuſtified: con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned, that thou mightſt be ſaued: Died, that thou mightſt liue: and calles for euery one tbat is weary and heauy loaden to come vnto him, and he will eaſe them.</p>
            <p>The third hinderer is vnskilfulneſſe in the carde, ignorance in ayming, and rudeneſſe in guiding:
<note place="margin">Math. 11.28.</note> for by this meanes, he may roaue at random, miſſe the hauen, and hinder his iourny:
<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.</note> Blinde <hi>Sampſon</hi> cannot finde the Pillars vnleſſe he be guided
<note place="margin">Acts. 9.</note> nor <hi>Saule</hi> Damaſcus vnleſſe he be directed but if the blind leade the blind, both fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to the ditch, and may be drowned. Not vnlike vnto this temporall blindeneſſe is the ſpirituall darkeneſſe of ignorance and infidilitie. For the ignorant goe<pb facs="tcp:17077:9"/>they know not whether, they walke in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they are very fooles, they are like the blind Sirians: they rowe among ther ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and there voyage is diſtruction.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 12</note> Seeke then for knowledge, Chriſt is the light:
<note place="margin">Prou.</note> bee skilfull in the carde, his word is the lanther:
<note place="margin">Iob. 4.</note> walke not in darkeneſſe, Chriſt is the way, drowne not in error, his worde is the truth.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 8,</note> To know God is life euerlaſting <hi>Ignoratiô ſcripturarum eſt ignoratio Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 12.</note> to be vnskilfull in the ſcriptures, is to be ignorant of Chriſt. Theſe are <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder: <hi>Dauids</hi> key, and will leade thee into all truth, without theſe thou art like the So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>domites looking for Lots houſe, the Iewes ſee king for Chriſt, the Pilot rouing at the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen but cannot hitte it.
<note place="margin">Iohn 17.</note> For the ſcriptures are our ſword, balla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, rule, ſquare &amp; dore that opens to vs the knowledge of God and conducts vs to euerlaſting happineſſe.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding albeit the ſcripture be a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle that burneth moſt brightly and the ſun that ſhineth moſt clearely yet they are not ſo vnto the blind, the hid, the dead, but only vnto him, whoſe darknes is inlightned, whoſe eares are vnſtopped, and whoſe eies are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to heare, to ſee, to beleeue the worde of<pb facs="tcp:17077:9"/>truth. The Iſralites hard the thunder but ſaw not God, the two diſciples hard &amp; ſaw Chriſt but knew not Ieſus, before their eies were opened. Infidility is a ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e that muſt be remoued, a cloud that muſt be diſperſed, &amp; a death that muſt be quickened, He that is troubled with this diſeaſe hath hands with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out feeling, eares without hearing, &amp; eyes without ſeeing.
<note place="margin">Aug.</note> O then let vs aske, ſeeke, and knocke for faith.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.5.9.</note> For faith is the inlightning of the mind: the victorie ouer the world: &amp; the gate wherby God enters into our harts it is the ſtar that leads the wiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Chriſt the woman to her groat: and the Prodigall child to his father.
<note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> It is the light: by which we walk:
<note place="margin">Luke. 15.</note> the life, by which we liue, the ſheild be which we are defended, &amp; the Cinoſura be which we ſayle, without this we ſhoot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the butte:
<note place="margin">Cor. 2.5.</note> run beſide the goale, and row beſide the hauen.</p>
            <p>Forthly as <hi>Noes</hi> Arke receiued al kind of creatures:
<note place="margin">Genneſ. 7.</note> the ſhip beareth al ſorts of bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dens: ſo doth man all manner of miſerie.
<note place="margin">Eurip.</note> For what is life but violence &amp; griefe: the body but a ſepulchre, the figure but fetters, birth but earth, and to liue but to die, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> cals man vnhappy,
<hi>Antiphanes</hi> death. <pb facs="tcp:17077:10"/>ſtipendary <hi>Nazinanze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a race, of vnſtabilitie, borne to laboure, and brought vp to miſerie, euen pleaſure breedes paine, welth woe &amp; ſinging ſighing, ſo that
<hi>Menander prefers</hi> all creatures before man for happines, whoſe ioy is but ſorrow, whoſe mirth is but griefe &amp; whoſe whole life but wretched miſerie: our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort is in God our goodnes Chriſt our captaine and heauen our happie hauen.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, as the ſhip is in continuall danger of waues, windes, gulfes, or rockes, ſo is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s life of ſin, ſickenes miſerie, and miſfortune, both ſea and land water, and earth, all are full of miſchefe, paine, trouble, ill, harme &amp; hurt: in ſuch ſorts as the poets add theſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithits to the ſea and ſay;ling, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtuous, boi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>strus, froward, dangerous, as they that ſaile the ſea can well recount the dangers of the ſame.
<note place="margin">Colaſ. 3. Gal. 5. Acts. 27.</note> But tent ines more ſtrang titles giue the ſcriptures vnto man, as inordinate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, couitous, wrathful, angrie, malitious curſed, proud, ſeditious, drunken, hating, murderous, yea what not? So that as a ſhip in daunger of drowning muſt be helped, by vnloading, ſtopping, pumping or anchoring ſo muſt man in this perilous world. When <hi>Pauls</hi> ſbip was in hazard by tempeſt, they<pb facs="tcp:17077:10"/>lightened the burden, eaſed the veſſell and caſt out the very tackling. And when thy ſhip is in daunger and loaden with the cares of the world, feare of death and pleaſure of ſin, thy remedy is to eaſe it by faith, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and good workes which <hi>Abraham Dauid, Peter,</hi> and the reſt did.</p>
            <p>Secondly the leaking ſhipe muſt be men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, and thy ſinfull ſoule amended. The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will drowne the ſhip, and ſin will ſmite thy ſoul, water muſt be kept out by ſtopping and ſin by riſiſting. for euery aſſent the ſoule giues to Sathan, ſin, the world and the fleſh is like a fearefull rift in a craſed veſſell: <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes</hi> reſemble great waues and cloſe rifts: ſome being great and manifeſt, others cloſe and ſecret. The firſt like mightie waues wil ſwallow vs vp quickely the ſecond like hid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den rifts will ſinke vs ſuddenly, Sathan ſuggeſted, <hi>Eue</hi> delighted, <hi>Adam</hi> conſented and all were drowned, <hi>Tecum prius ergo voluta haec anime, ante tubas, galeatum ſero duelli paenitet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3. Iuuen. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>VVhen the ſtead is ſtolne it will be to late to ſhut the doore, when the houſe is burnt to poure on water, and vvhen the battle is done to put on harneſſe. Stop ſin in the thought<pb facs="tcp:17077:11"/>refiſt it in the entrance, it is a ſerpent, bruſe it on the head; a cocatriſe, kill it in the egge: and a wolfe, diſtroy it in the litter. Sin is thy enemie looke vnto thy waies, a thiefe looke vnto the doores: a Dalila looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſoule: thy ſenſes are thy porters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware they be not beguiled. Be thy ſins ſecret yet a ſecret ſtab will take away thy life: bee they hidden, yet hidden poyſon will rob thee of thy ſelfe: be they ſmale, <hi>de guttis mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis implentur flumina</hi> yet ſmall drops makes great flouds and drown much ground and therefore ſtoppe it out betimes.
<note place="margin">Aug.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly he muſt pumpe to eaſe the ſhip of water: and man repent to eaſe his ſoule of ſin.<note place="margin">Eſa. 38.</note>
               <hi>Hezechias</hi> plague ſore muſt haue a plaiſter of figges to draw the poyſon from his heart:
<note place="margin">Luke. 3.9.</note> and thy peſtilent ſin a plaiſter of Gods word, to keepe the infections from thy ſoule.
<note place="margin">Tim. 1.4.</note> The dropſie body requires a ſweate to purge out humors, and mans dropſie ſoule the feare of God to driue out ſin. <hi>Naaman</hi> muſt be waſht ſeauen times in Iordan to cleanſe his body and we be bathed ſeauen times in repentance to ſcoure our ſoules. The ſurfetting ſtomacke muſt haue a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to helpe his bodie: and man true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion<pb facs="tcp:17077:11"/>to eaſe his ſoule, The ſickely body muſt keepe a diet to preſerue his health and the penitent man muſt abſtaine from ſin to ſaue his ſoule, vnto which if he add exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of good workes he ſhalbe happie.
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly in danger the marriner will ly at Anker for his ſaftie: ſo muſt man in the ſea of this world for his ſecuritie. His An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers muſt be faith, hope, and prayer: the ground muſt be the Trinitie: then will the Anker hold, and the ground neuer faile: For we haue Gods promiſe &amp; his othe that by two things, vvherein it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that God ſhould lie we might haue ſtrong conſolation, which haue our refuge to hold faſt the hope, that is ſet before vs, which we haue as an Anker of the ſoule both ſure and ſtedfaſt. And if God be with vs, let windes, waues, rockes, ſin, Sathan, &amp; the world, fret, fume, blow, all ſhall not hurt vs.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, and laſtly: as the toſſed ſeafea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man wearied with waues, withered with wind ruſhed with rockes, and greened with gulfes wil make mirth and melodie at his ſafe arriual in the earthly haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo much more the chriſtian ſayler, whoſe ſhip is him<pb facs="tcp:17077:12"/>ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> whoſe windes, waues, gulfes, &amp; rocks are his proſperous, ſiniſter, troubles, tempta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, trangreſſions,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.</note> and whoſe hauen is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which he vewes a far of, ſalutes out of the ſea, ſighes after with heauie grones, &amp; praiſe for dayly with watred eies, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue with ioy, embrace with hymmes, and retaine with euerlaſting praiſe his ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed entrance in the happie heauens.
<note place="margin">Apoc. 22.</note> How willing where the Saints to die: <hi>Paule</hi> to be diſſolued, and <hi>Dauid</hi> to be with God? This makes the good man dy ſinging like the ſwan liue praying with the ſaints: and cry ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning dravve me, drawe me with the Church, <hi>Ocurramus, ſequamur</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambros: Curramus non paſſibus ſed afflictioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> ſaith <hi>Barnard</hi> let vs run, follow, flie, here is not happineſſe: let vs haſt, poſt, ſaile with hearts, with hands, with grones, ſobs, and ſighes, there is felicitie, where whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou arriueſt, thou ſhalt haue Father Son, and ſpirit to receiue thee, Angels, ſaints, and all the heauenly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ier, to imbrace thee, The bleſſed Trinitie for Chriſt his promiſe to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward thee, with a crowne, kingdome, thro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e happie, heauenly and eternall where paine is neuer felt, groning neuer heard, ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:17077:12"/>neuer ſeene and euill neuer feared: but there ſhall be youth without age: life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out death, health without ſickenes, and true felicitie for euer without end: the which we pray for, we labour for, and we ſaile for.</p>
            <p>The way and method, I haue opened in this ſhort treatis for a confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the rich, comfort of the poore, and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation vnto all.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17077:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17077:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE ART OF CHRISTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sayling. Or, A comfortable Treatiſe, written on theſe words of the Prophet Dauid, in the 55. Pſalme. 22, 23. Verſes.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Caſt thy burden vpon the Lord, and hee shall nourish thee: He will not ſuffer the righteous to fall for euer. And thou, O God, ſhalt bring them downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pit of corruption, &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lus mouent exempla quàm verba.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregory.</note> Examples doe moue more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> precepts, and a good life, then a good leſſon. For, <hi>Homines facilius ad benefaciendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, exemplis, quàm verbis, inuitantur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origin.</note> Men are incited ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:17077:14"/>by workes, then by words: and by liues, then by lawes to do wel. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dauid,</hi> inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to preferre a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, firſt propounds his practiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, <hi>haec iuſtitia eſt, vt quod alterum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere velles, tute prius ipſe incipias.</hi> This is the law of iuſtice, to practiſe that wee would haue others performe, &amp; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin that our ſelues wherein we would haue others to go forwards: And hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſhalt thou be, if <hi>Dauids</hi> hazzard be thy happines, his practiſe, thy preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and his cure in extremitie, thy care in aduerſitie, to caſt vpon the Lord. For being perſecuted by <hi>Saul,</hi> hee wiſheth wings like a Doue, in the 6. verſe. But <hi>hac via non ſuccedente,</hi> preuayling not this wayes, hee betakes him vnto his prayers, and cries vnto the Lord in the 17. verſe; there is his practiſe: and his ſoule was deliuered in peace, in the 19. verſe; there is thy warrant. Now for thy inſtruction, this Pſalme is by the Greeks intituled,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. A Pſalme of Dauid, to giue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Or, <hi>ode didaſcalica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tremeli.</note> wherein <hi>Dauid,</hi> or God by <hi>Dauid,</hi> playes the maſter, and thou (if thou feareſt God)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17077:14"/>muſt be the ſcholler. Or laſtly <hi>Maſkille Dauid,</hi> according to the Hebrewes, as who ſhould ſay, In this Pſalme is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, <hi>Doctrina ſitu digniſsima:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sadel. in Pſal. 32.</note> A doctrine worth thy knowledge for thy vnderſtanding: and wee may adde a practiſe worthy imitation for thy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. For when proſperitie on thy right hand, ſhall vpbraid thee with, <hi>Quis tu es?</hi> alas thou art graſſe, and thy glorie as the flower of the field:
<note place="margin">Eſai. 40.6.</note> then mayeſt thou caſt this burden on the Lord, &amp; ſay with <hi>Dauid:</hi> How euer it be, yet God is good.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.1.</note> And when aduerſity ſhall demaund, <hi>Vnde es?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.9.</note> thou art of the earth, and to the earth thou muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.
<note place="margin">Iob. 17.14.</note> Corruption was thy mother, &amp; wormes are thy ſiſters. Thy dayes are ſwifter then the weauers ſhittle,
<note place="margin">Iob. 7.6.</note> and for thy abiding, thou haſt not whereon to lay thy head:
<note place="margin">Math. 8.20.</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caſt this burden, &amp;c. and make it knowne with holy <hi>Iob,</hi> that naked cameſt thou out of thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, and naked ſhalt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.
<note place="margin">Iob. 1.20.</note> For <hi>dant ſuperi cuncta vel aufe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pindarus</note> The Lord giueth, and the Lord taketh away. And yet ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 127 3.</note> The Lord hath done great things, yea<pb facs="tcp:17077:15"/>great things for vs already. Though vertue reiect thee with this queſtion, <hi>Qua ſemita huc accedes?</hi> it is a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to clime the tree of vertue, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for thee that art borne in ſinne, and conceiued in iniquitie:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5</note> whoſe righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes is like a filthie clout,
<note place="margin">Eſai. 64.6.</note> and all the cogitations of thy heart are prone to euill euermore:
<note place="margin">Gen. 6.5.</note> Yet caſt this burden likewiſe vpon the Lord, and ſay with <hi>Dauid, Miſericordia Domini plena eſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi> The earth is full of the goodnes &amp; louing kindnes of the Lord: and with <hi>Auguſtine, Plus vult ille miſereri, quàm nos a miſeria liberari:</hi> The Lord is more willing to ſhew mercie, then we are to receiue it. And when vice ſhall inuade thee, with <hi>Qua cautela huc recedes?</hi> thou art now in the cuſtodie of ſinne, and fettered with the bonds of iniquitie: if thou wouldeſt breake priſon, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looſe thy fetters, thou muſt firſt binde the ſtrong man.
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.14.</note> But alas, thou art weake,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.30.</note> and not able ſo much as to wil, thou art dead in thy ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2.1</note> and how wilt thou deliuer thy ſelfe? then caſt this burden alſo vpon the Lord, and ſay with
<hi>Nehemias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehemi. 4.20.</note> The Lord ſhal fight
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17077:15"/>for vs. And with <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 8.31</note> If God bee with vs, who can be againſt vs? And with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 3.6</note> The Lord is my ſaluation, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not be afraid for ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand that beſet mee round about. Though that heauen denies thee with <hi>Quo titulo introitum vindicas?</hi> Alas, thou art fleſh: for what is of the fleſh, is fleſh:
<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.6</note> but fleſh and bloud cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the kingdome of heauen:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15</note> Yet mayeſt thou caſt this burden vpon the Lord, and ſay with Bernard: <hi>Puto iam ſpernere me non poterit Chriſtus, os de oſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus meis, &amp; caro de carne mea.</hi> I know that Chriſt my redeemer will not now reiect me, that ſo dearely bought mee: who for this cauſe became bone of my bones, and fleſh of my fleſh, that he might bring me vnto his heauenly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe. And though hell and ſinne do make challenge to thee, with <hi>Quo iure exitum aduocas?</hi> deſcend to hell, for he that committeth ſinne, is of the diuell:
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.8.</note> but thou art altogether ſinfull, take therefore the broad way that leades vnto hell:
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.13.</note> behold, the Angels defie thee, heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denies thee, vertue reiects thee, vice retaines thee, and the diuell
<pb facs="tcp:17077:16"/>will haue thee: yet caſt this burden likewiſe vpon the Lord, and ſay, <hi>Nihil odiſti eorum quae feciſti?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſd. 11</note> thou hateſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that thou haſt made. But behold (ſaith God) all ſoules are mine: and therefore take me, that am the worke of thy owne handes. And thus we are led by the title of this Pſalme, to tune <hi>Dauids</hi> Harpe vnto Chriſts muſike, being like vnto the loade-ſtar, that in the darke night co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducts the wandring traueller to his wiſhed hauen: ſo this, the wearied Chriſtian, vnto the hauen of his ſure deliuerance. For albeit the browne diuell penury oppreſſe thee, and the blacke diuell of perſecution purſue thee; though the world bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped about thee, and the heauens bee banded againſt thee: yet this will leade thee vnto the true deliuerer, which is the Lord thy God, thy true ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil</hi> vpon this text compares man vnto a true penitentiary, cloathed in ſackcloth, and apparelled with a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of hayre, going into Gods houſe weeping, but returning from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence laughing; going heauily burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17077:16"/>but returning altogether ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Yet <hi>Auguſtine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> comming more nigh the letter, compares man in this world, to a loade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhip ſayling vpon the boiſtrous ſeas, drawing the warrant of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon, firſt from the word <hi>haſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecke,</hi> which ſignifieth caſt, as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner that caſts his anker. Secondly, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>mote</hi> of <hi>mute, fluctuatio, a fluctibus.</hi> The Septuagints tranſlate it
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifieth
<hi>procella,</hi> a ſtorme by ſea: from whence comes <hi>ſalum,</hi> which <hi>Ennius</hi> makes <hi>ſalus,</hi> and ſignifieth the ſea. Thirdly, from Beer, whereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Greeke
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>puteus,</hi> a wel with water. And thus compared, the text affordeth vs theſe three partes: Firſt, a caſting or lying at anker, from
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>racta ſicut anchoram in mari,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyrain Peter. 1.5</note> caſt as an anker is caſt in the ſea. The ſecond thing, is, his arriuing in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, from
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. He will not ſuffer the righteous to fall for euer: <hi>videris fluctuari in mari iſto, ſed excipit te por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> Thou ſeemeſt to be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerouſly toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this ſea, but, the hauen that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues thee, yea <hi>portus tranquilliſſimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſſidori.</note> the moſt calme, and bleſſed hauen, that<pb facs="tcp:17077:17"/>will neuer deceiue thee. Thirdly, the ſhipwrack from <hi>veattah Elohim.</hi> Thou, O God, ſhalt bring them
<hi>in puteum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſionis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> into the pit of drowning or deſtruction, to teach vs that ſayle here in this world of calamitie, to caſt ſure vpon the ground of Gods prouidence, that we may arriue in the world to come, in the hauen of happineſſe, leſt we periſh with the wicked for neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Becauſe this world <hi>eſt vallis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia inter coelum, et infernum, quaſi inter montem vitae, &amp; monte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mortis.</hi> A valley placed in the middeſt betweene hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and hell, as betweene the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life, and the mountaine of death. And becauſe this world is
<hi>via peccati, &amp; vmbra mortis, in qua pyrata diabolus recte gradientibus retia deceptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis expandit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. vol 1. ſerm. 13.</note> It is the way of ſin, and the ſhaddow of death, wherein the diuell the arch-pyrate, ſets his nets of murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring deceites, to entrap them that would walke in the wayes of Gods commaundements. And thus much of the introduction and interpretation of this ſcripture. Now to the parts as they lie in order: And firſt of our ankering,<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17077:17"/>contayned in theſe words: Caſt thy burden vpon the Lord, and hee ſhall nouriſh thee.</p>
            <p>This clauſe affords vnto vs theſe three things; Firſt, the ankers that we muſt caſt, and they are two: prayer and affiance. The ſecond is the ſhip that muſt bee ſtayed by theſe ankers, and that is
<hi>lehabhka,</hi> thy burden, thy burdened and wearied life. The third is the ground whereunto theſe ankers muſt bee faſtened, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they muſt bee caſt: and that is two-fold. Firſt, a generall ground, and that is God. Secondly, a more particular, and that is his prouidence: Caſt thy burden vpon the Lord, and he ſhall nouriſh thee.</p>
            <p>Now to the firſt, which is our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering. <hi>Selucus</hi> beeing expelled out of Babylon, &amp; returning by the helpe of
<hi>Ptolomy</hi> with a band of ſouldiers, as hee made haſte vnto the Citie, ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and ſtumbling, hurt his foote: whereat his friends ſomewhat agrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, reauing vp the ſtone, found a ring that was hidden vnder it, in which ring was engrauen the ſimilitude, and<pb facs="tcp:17077:18"/>forme of an Anker: which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting, ſuppoſed it to portend cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity. But hee being of another ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, cryed out vnto them with a lowd voyce, <hi>Bono animo eſtote omnes, nam qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terram calcamus, &amp; retenturi ſumus, &amp; poſſeſſuri:</hi> Be of good cheere, my friends, and fellowes; for this ground, whereon we now tread, as aliants and exiles, wee ſhall aſſuredly poſſeſſe, as heires and owners. And thus, that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, which they conſtrued to ſignifie captiuity, hee interpreted to pretend conqueſt, and ſecurity. In which ſence <hi>Plutarch</hi> vſeth
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for an anker, ſignifying ſecurity, making it with <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> the very reſcue of defence. And the Egyptian Hieroglyphickes, when they would deſcribe vnto vs, true ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or ſafegard, they painted a ſhip and an anker; noting vnto vs, that if aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity beſet vs in this world, as a tempeſt ſets vpon a ſhippe in the ſea, yet there was an Anker, a readie refuge, to ſtay vs from drowning.</p>
            <p>Now then, ſeeing man with his burden, is compared vnto a ſhip with his loade, and wee muſt aſſure our<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17077:18"/>ſelues, that heere we ſhall finde a ſea; therefore let vs prouide for our ſelues, a ſteady Anker, leſt wee bee ſuddenly inuaded with a ſtorme of boyſterous calamitie, and ſo periſh in our ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſecuritie: for
<hi>nauigamus in hac vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, quaſi per quoddam mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, vbi &amp; ventus est, &amp; procell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> non deſunt tentationum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. in Iohn. 14.</note> We ſayle in this life, as it were thorow a ſea, wherein there are both windes of aduerſity, and ſtormes of temptations: Here being but two ſeas to paſſe, <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum</hi> and <hi>rubrum:</hi> the dead ſea, and the redde ſea. The firſt is <hi>mare pacaetum,</hi> a ſea calme, without ſurges, and the ſaylers heerein, are worldlings: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called calme, becauſe dead: and therefore dead, becauſe the ſaylers herein are already ſmitten with death, being ſlayne by ſin, and murdered by iniquity: for ſin is
<hi>gladius, ſerpens, vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> a ſword that wounds the ſoule; a ſerpent, that ſtings the conſcience, and poyſon, that kils Chriſt the true life of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, is <hi>turbidum,</hi> a rough &amp; troubleſome ſea, and the marriners herein, are the louers of God, red with<pb facs="tcp:17077:19"/>the bloud of the Saynts. For heere <hi>funditur ater vbique cruor, crudelis, vbique luctus, vbique pauor, &amp; plurima mortis imago.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. Tac. in Ner. perſecut.</note> Here is ſhed euery where the bloud of Chriſtians; here is heard in all places, the lamentation of Saints; here is feare, and the image of death ſeene, and ſeazing vpon the liues of holy men, and Gods ſeruants. Theſe are the two wayes whereby the deuill aſſaults &amp; ſets vpon men in this world,
<hi>perſuaſione, vt molliat; perſecutione, vt frangat:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> by perſwaſion to winne, and vanquiſh man by fayre meanes, as hee ſet vpon Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.8,9.</note> offring him all the kingdomes of the world, and the glory of them, if he would worſhip him:
<note place="margin">Iob. 2.7.</note> or by perſecution, to break &amp; bend him with foule meanes, as he inuaded <hi>Iob,</hi> ſmiting him with ſore boyles, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſole of his foot, to the crowne of his head, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pel him to blaſpheme God, and forſake his Creator. <hi>Quid igitur facies? Excita Iefum, &amp; dic, Magiſter, perimus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. 49 tract. vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Iohn.</note> What is now to bee done in this caſe? Euen that which the Diſciples did when the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt aroſe in the ſea, and the ſhippe was couered with waues: They came vnto<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17077:19"/>Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 8.25.</note> and awoke him, ſaying, Maſter, ſaue vs, we periſh.</p>
            <p>This is that anker, which the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemiſts paint tied vnto a ſtrong rope, with this title or mot, <hi>Tutum te littore ſiſtam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Claudius Paradin.</note> I will place thee ſafe vpon the ſhore. Signifying vnto vs, that our hope of ſaluation, being faſtened vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, who is our ſureſt ſafegard, and ſauing refuge, whereunto we muſt continually flie in all our troubles and aduerſities, it will bring vs vnto the hauen of ſafe deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and quiet happineſſe.</p>
            <p>This anker wee are put in minde to haue in continuall readineſſe, if by no other name, yet by this, that wee are called ſaylers, whoſe condition is ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous, and eſtate ſo dangerous, as
<hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carſis</hi> could not tell whether he ſhould account them <hi>inter viuos, vel mortuos:</hi> among the liuing, or the dead. And if we will needs haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be numbred amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the liuing, yet the fartheſt they are from death, is but <hi>ſpiſſitudo tabula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nauticarum,</hi> the thickneſſe of a three inched boord: a moſt brickle &amp; lamentable caſe: yet were we happy, if<pb facs="tcp:17077:20"/>our veſſell wherein wee fayle in this world, were thus ſtrong, as is the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners boate. But alas, it is much more fraile and fickle: being compared ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnto a flower,
<note place="margin">Iob. 14.</note> 
               <hi>vita in carne, flos in foeno:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Am. vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Luke.</note> as the flower in the graſſe, ſo is this life in the fleſh: ſometimes to a ſhaddow, ſometimes to a reede, yea, ſometimes to vanitie it ſelfe.
<note place="margin">Pſa. 144.</note> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the enemies that daily aſſault our veſſell, are much more mighty, &amp; enuious, then thoſe things, which are obnoxius to the ſailers ſhip: albeit they be <hi>ignis aqua,</hi> and <hi>hoſtes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> fire, water, and enemies: then the which, in their fury, there is no earthly thing more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: for here is <hi>concupiſcentia, cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, &amp; opera:</hi> concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; thoughts, words, and wicked works, like fire to burne it, water to drowne it, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to deſtroy it. Fire, but it is the wild fire of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cals for the trouble,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; for the hurt it brings with it <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> flat ſinne: and Saint
<hi>Iames</hi> compares it,
<note place="margin">Ia. 1.14.</note> for the ſubtilneſſe of it, vnto a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pter, and for the cruelneſſe of it, vnto a fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, becauſe
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it tempts &amp; drawes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17077:20"/>vs from that which is good, and then,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it ſnares and ouertakes vs before wee be aware. And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> makes a threefold kind thereof.
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.16.</note> Firſt,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life: yea this fire is ſo much more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous then the elementary fire, by how much it is more ſecrete, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. Wherefore <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth it a hidden fire, crying out, Who vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth his faults? and coſting the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of prayer for his deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, calleth vpon God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.13.</note> ſaying, O cleanſe me from my ſecret faults. To ſecond this, there comes the water of actuall ſinne, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times like vnto a boyſtrous ſea, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one waue ouertakes another: ſo is the ſinne of thought, ſometimes follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed by the ſin of words, &amp; ſometimes both thoughts &amp; words are acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with wicked works: otherwhiles this water of actuall ſin enters our ſhip by drops, and makes a great flood within our ſoules: for
<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>de guttis minutis flumina implentur:</hi> and <hi>humor per rimas influens nauem confundit:</hi> great floods ariſe of<pb facs="tcp:17077:21"/>little drops: &amp;, water iſſuing in by ſmall riftes, drownes and ſinkes the ſhip. O therefore (ſayth the wiſe man)
<note place="margin">Eccleſi.</note> adde not ſin vnto ſin, for this is but to adde fire vnto fire, when we would haue the firſt fire to be quenched; and water vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to water, when we would haue the firſt water dryed. If we would know how this water of ſin ſokes in by little and little into our rifty ſoules, <hi>Iſidore</hi> makes it manifeſt vnto thee:
<hi>Suggeſtio parit co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitationem: cogitatio, delectationem: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectatio, conſenſum: conſenſus, actionem: actio, conſuetudinem: conſuetudo, neceſii<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: neceſsitas, malam mortem: mala mors, da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nationem: damnatio, poenam aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam in Gehenna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, there is offred a ſuggeſtion: a ſuggeſtion ingenders a thought or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation: cogitation breedes delight: delight begets conſent: and conſent brings foorth the action: one action muſt haue another: and many actions turne vnto cuſtome: cuſtome cannot be left; and ſo it produceth neceſsitie: neceſsity that muſt not be repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of; and ſo it brings vs to an euill death: an euill death, that drawes vs to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation:<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17077:21"/>and damnation, to the eternall paines of hell. And thus ſinne entring in by a little hole, yet ſtings to death: and what doth it aduantage thee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou bee ſmitten with a broade ſword that makes an apparant wound, or ſtabbed with a ſmall poinyard that makes but a ſmall breach; ſeeing thou art aſſured to die as well by the one as the other? Wherefore let this be a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat for vs to take heede of all ſinnes: for if they be great, the world will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs: if ſmall, either the poyſon thereof will kill vs, or the number of them will deſtroy vs. But leaſt the fire ſhould looſe her nature, &amp; ſo not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume this ſhippe; and the water ſhould forget her moiſture, &amp; ſo not drowne it: the enemie will ſet his hand to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it; euen the enemy which is called the Diuell, with his great army of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and powers, vnder whoſe banner doe fight, men and ſpirits, the fleſh and the world. For there is a neuer ending warre betweene him and vs. The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld whereof was God himſelfe, who ſowed this diſſention, and proclaimed<pb facs="tcp:17077:22"/>this warre ſaying: <hi>veepah Aſhith bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15,</note> I will put enmitie betweene thee and the woman, and betweene thy ſeed and her ſeed.
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> Hence hee is called our aduerſarie, and that no ſmall one, but that great red Dragon, euen that Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon that fought in heauen:
<note place="margin">Apocal. 12.</note> the olde Serpent and Satan which deceiueth all the world; who ſet vpon God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>Adam</hi> in paradiſe, and Chriſt in the wilderneſſe, and will neuer leaue vs, which alas haue neither force to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him, nor wit to diſcerne him.
<note place="margin">Bernard. 7 ſerm. de aduent. domini.</note>
               <hi>Si diſcernere volumus inter bonum &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum decipimur, ſi tentamus facere bonum deficimur, ſi conamur reſiſtere malo deijci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</hi> If we would diſcerne betweene good and euill, we are deceiued: If we go about to do good, we quickly faint: and if we indeuour to reſiſt ſinne, we are eaſily ouercome. A fight moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and warre moſt vnequal: he ſtrong, we weake: he full of experience, we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither vnexpert: he ſubtill, we ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: he valiant, and we full of coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Onely this remaines to keepe vs from deſtroying in this dangerous bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17077:22"/>namely, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: to let downe and caſt this holy anchor, fall to prayer, and call vpon our God. For <hi>vt nauem ancora: ſic oratio vitam firmam reddit.</hi> As the anchor ſtaies the ſhippe, and keepes it ſteadie againſt winde and weather: ſo doth prayer maintaine the Chriſtian from periſhing by the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Satan, and inuaſions of the wicked world. For the Diuell is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> vnto a Lyon: and ſaith <hi>Gaudentius Merula:</hi> As a Lyon is diſcomfited at the ſight of a Cocke, and at his crowing betakes him vnto his heeles: ſo doth Satan that murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lyon, both ſtand in feare when the godly man appeareth, and flies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way when he betakes him vnto his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. The Diuell is a venemous Serpent, and ſaith <hi>Iſidore: Muſtela bellatura cum Serpente: primo rutam comedit, cuius vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute &amp; odore contra venenum ſe munit: &amp; ſic ad bellum ſecura procedit.</hi> The Weafell going to fight with the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; firſt eates Rue, the ſmell and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue whereof, armes, and defendes her againſt the force of the poyſon, and<pb facs="tcp:17077:23"/>then ſhe goes boldly vnto the battell. So muſt we, who are continually inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned, and daily beſieged by Satan, and his army; firſt arme our ſelues with prayer, which will defend vs againſt Satans temptations, and then may we be bold to encounter the enemy, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſt his precept, and practiſe; who prayed himſelfe, ſaying: O my Father:
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.41</note> and likewiſe commaunded the ſame vnto his Diſciples, ſaying: Watch and pray, leaſt ye enter into temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For a prayer is <hi>ſacrificium Deo, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monibus flagellum;</hi> and <hi>oranti ſubſidium:</hi> a ſacrifice to God, a ſcourge for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, and a refuge, and a reſcue for him that prayeth. Firſt a ſacrifice vnto God, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the ſacrifice of praiſe;
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.15</note> that is, the fruit of their lippes, which confeſſe Gods name. This is that <hi>munus,</hi> that gift which Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Leper to offer vnto the Prieſt:
<note place="margin">Tertul. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Marſ. lib. 4.</note> namely, <hi>orationem &amp; gratiarum actiones</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Tertullian</hi>) prayer, and giuing of thankes. For <hi>ſicut Thimiama bene confectum delectat hominem odoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: ſic oratio iuſti ſuauis eſt ante Deum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſto.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17077:23"/>As ſweete perfume much delights the ſmell; ſo is the prayer of the righteous man, much pleaſing in the noſtrels of God. The altar whereon we offer this ſacrifice, is <hi>Altare coeleſte:</hi> our faith, which <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calleth an heauenly altar, whereon our prayers being offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Chriſt (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) receiues them, and purifying them, commends them vnto his father, vnto whom for Chriſt his ſake they are acceptable. Wherefore he that offereth vnto God <hi>ſacrificium orationis,</hi> muſt diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue three things:
<note place="margin">Bernard. Epiſt. ad frat. de mont. Dei.</note>
               <hi>Quis, Cui, Quid.</hi> Firſt, who is he that offereth, and he muſt be
<hi>pauper ſpiritu,</hi> the poore in ſpirit. Secondly, to whom, and that is to God, vnto whom he muſt <hi>ſurſum cor,</hi> lift vp his heart. Thirdly, what he muſt offer, and that is a right qualified prayer, proceeding from true ſaith, and feruent loue: and then God wil receiue thy ſacrifice, and the Diuels will bee much tormented with it, which is the ſecond benefit which followeth heartie and earneſt prayer.
<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> For <hi>per orationem vincuntur demonia,</hi> the Diuels are caſt<pb facs="tcp:17077:24"/>out, and ſubdued by prayer. By this was the Lunaticke perſon deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that tormenting Diuell, which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times caſt him into the fire, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into the water, becauſe this kinde goeth not out but by prayer and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.
<note place="margin">Mat. 17.21</note> Neither is this all that we receiue by prayer, but we are defended alſo by it from all aſſaults, and temptations.
<note place="margin">Ambroſe.</note> For it is <hi>bonum ſcutum, quo omnia ſpicula aduerſarij repelluntur:</hi> that good ſhield whereby all the dartes of the aduerſarie are repelled. It is
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Chriſtian mans phyſicke, againſt all ſpirituall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.
<note place="margin">Theodoret</note> If we be in <hi>medijs aquis:</hi> in the middeſt of the waters, this is our ſafeſt deliuerance, and as it was vnto <hi>Ionas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ionas. 3.2.</note> who being in the bottome of the ſea, and the belly of the Whale, cried vnto the Lord, and he heard him. If we be in <hi>igne,</hi> in the fire, by this we ſhall be deliuered:
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> as were the three children in the middeſt of the firie furnace, who cried vnto the Lord, and he deliuered them. If we be <hi>inter medios Leones:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the middeſt of the Lyons,
<note place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> as was <hi>Daniel</hi> in the middeſt of the Lyons<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17077:24"/>denne, who cried vnto the Lord, and he deliuered him. This is Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and <hi>Dauids</hi> practiſe. For the firſt ſaith God:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> Call vpon me in the day of trouble, and I will deliuer thee. And for the ſecond, ſaith <hi>Dauid:</hi> out of the deepes haue I called vnto thee O Lord, and thou deliueredſt me.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.</note> If we be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by our enemies, by this we ſhal haue deliuerance, as was <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kings. 6.18.</note> who prayed vnto the Lord, and was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>vertit ſe eo, vbi omnes verum auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium inuenerunt, ſcilicet, ad orationem, quae vnica deſper atorum ancora eſt.</hi> And laſtly, if a whole army be ſet againſt vs, by this we ſhall ouercome them;
<note place="margin">Numb. 17</note> as did <hi>Moſes</hi> the Amalekites, who pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the Lorde, and was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
<note place="margin">Gloſſa.</note> For, <hi>plus valet vnus ſanctus orando, quam innumeri peccatores praeliando,</hi> one good man will do more good by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then an innumerable number of ſinners by fighting. Thus in the army of <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> the Philoſopher, at the prayers of a band of Chriſtians, God ſent water, and things neceſſarie for the army,
<note place="margin">Xiphilinus</note> togither with a mightie
<pb facs="tcp:17077:25"/>tempeſt, to the deſtruction of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy. And thus the kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> praying againſt his perſecuting enemies, ſaith: That the Lord thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from heauen, hee ſent out his arrowes, and ſcattered them; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed his lightnings, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.13,14.</note> God hath called our ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my abroad, the enemy is encamped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs, and hath ſhaken his ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs: and who can tell, whether the Lord will likewiſe ſhew mercie vpon our prayers? The Heathens could giue this report of the Chriſtians:
<note place="margin">Capitolin. in Marco.</note> 
               <hi>nihil eſſe, quod ij qui Chriſtiani nominantur, preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus à Deo impetrare non poſſent.</hi> That there is nothing, which the Chriſtian man by his prayers, may not obtaine at Gods hand. This was it that ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the cruell perſecutors in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church: as <hi>Plinius Iunior,</hi> writing to <hi>Traian,</hi> about the profeſſours of Chriſtianitie, acquites them of all faults and offences, both againſt Prince and people, excepting this one: <hi>quod ante Lucanos hymnos in cuinſdam hominis lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Palaeſtina crucifixus erat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantarent.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:17077:25"/>That they ſung hymnes and pſalmes before breake of day, touching thankeſgiuing and praiſe, for Chriſt which was crucified in Paleſtina. O has <hi>Plinie</hi> liued in theſe daies, he would neuer haue found this fault with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: among whom the name of God, and his ſonne Chriſt, is more abuſed to his diſhonour, then rightly vſed for his praiſe and honour. Notwithſtanding, neuer was there more neede of prayer, then in theſe daies, wherein faith is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgotten, and charitie waxeth too colde: wherein the world is turned vpſidowne, and Chriſt begins to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vs to our account: and wherein God and Satan, haue this long time bent their bowes againſt vs. God hath bent his bow, but it is the bow of long ſuffering; the wood whereof is <hi>iuſtitia,</hi> iuſtice; the ſtring
<hi>miſericordia,</hi> mercie; and the arrowe <hi>vindicta,</hi> reuenge: and if we ſtil abuſe his patience by our ſins, as we haue begun, and deſpiſe his long ſuffering by our iniquities, as we go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: then muſt needs his iuſtice for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get his mercie, and ſend the arrowe of
<pb facs="tcp:17077:26"/>reuenge againſt vs. Happy therefore ſhall they be that can caſt this anchor of faith and prayer vpon Chriſt:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.12.</note> For when his wrath ſhall ſuddenly burne, then bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him. The Diuell likewiſe hath bent his bowe, but it is the bowe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death &amp; deſtruction; the wood whereof is <hi>malitia,</hi> the Diuels malice: the ſtring <hi>experientia,</hi> his experience: and the ſhafte
<hi>temptatio,</hi> alluring and deceitfull temptation, which he often lets flie round about vs, wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſome, and killing others. This man with pride; that with gluttony; another with couetouſneſſe; and a fourth with periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Filling the world full with all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, fornication, wickednes, maliciouſneſſe, enuie, murther, deceit, debate, and what not, to bring vs all vnto confuſion. O beloued, neuer more ſhooting, and neuer leſſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: neuer more dartes, and yet few or none applies his ſhield. For who now moiſteneth his prayers, with the teares of true repentance; thereby to quench the firie dartes of Satan? <hi>O lacrymae quo<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17077:26"/>fugiſtis? redite obſecro redite lacrymae, flete me coelum &amp; terra. Lugete me omnes creaturae, &amp; me plorate omnia elementa. peccaui enim crudeliter; lapſus ſum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiter; cecidi mirabiliter, Nullus eſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vitiorum, à quo non contraxi contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſiodore Dial<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flentis, lib.
1. cap. 41.</note> High time it is, to crie with the penitent perſon: O teares, whither are you fled? ô ſighes, whither are you gone? Come againe ye teares, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ô ye ſobs. Come heauen, come earth and bewaile me. O ye creatures lament ouer me. For I haue ſinned cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly: I haue fallen grieuouſly: there is no ſinne wherewith I am not fowly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted. Did not the heauens raine at <hi>Elias</hi> prayer?
<note place="margin">1. King. 18</note> and the rocke ſend foorth flouds at <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtroke?
<note place="margin">Exod. 17.6</note> and ſhall God ſmite, Satan wound, and yet we bee without prayers of repentance? The Poets report of
<hi>Hector,</hi> that ſo long as he liued, Troy could not be deſtroyed: calling him <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the immoueable, and inexpugnable pillar of Troy. But much more may it be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the beleeuing ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er bindeth God to doe good vnto the<pb facs="tcp:17077:27"/>countrey. As was <hi>Lot</hi> vnto the Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, of whom God witneſſeth that he could doe nothing againſt them, ſo long as <hi>Lot</hi> liued amongſt them.
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.22</note> In what a lamentable caſe then, is that countrey and place, wherein there is no <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 22.30</note> no man of prayer to ſtand in the gappe before God for the land? A token that God intends a preſent pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to fall vpon that countrey: and on the contrarie, where God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth the ſpirit of prayer, he will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe giue a bleſſing of mercie. For this cauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> ioynes prayer and mercie togither, ſaying:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.20.</note> Praiſed be God, which hath not put backe my prayer, nor hid his mercie from me, noting prayer to be the eſpeciall meanes, whereby God will conferre a benefit vpon a people. Becauſe,
<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>quamdiu Deus non tollit à te o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem tuam, non amouebit à te miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam ſuam:</hi> ſo long as God depriues thee not of the ſpirit of prayer, he will not denie thee his mercifull kindneſſe. Seeing therefore that by prayer
<note place="margin">Caſſianus.</note> 
               <hi>Ira Dei ſuſpenditur, venia procuratur, poena refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur,</hi> and <hi>proemiorum largitas impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17077:27"/>wee haue acceſſe vnto God; the priſoner to intreat the Iudge; the Iudge is mooued to mercie, and his mercie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueth him with all kinde of bleſſings. O therefore prouide in time while it is to day for this happy anchor, if not to ſtay thy tottering ſelfe in this miſerable world; yet to defend thy toſſed coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, from the boiſtrous inuaſion of the open foe, and the deceitfull practiſe of thy traiterous friend. But becauſe this ſea is verie boiſterous, waue following waue, and tempeſt running after tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt. It is not amiſſe to follow <hi>Pynda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> his counſell, eſpecially
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in this winters night to looſe two an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors. The time was indeed, wherein man <hi>quaſi dies in gratia claruit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale. 35.18.</note> was as bright as the day, and as cleare as the ſunne, walking in the day light of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed grace. But being enwrapped in ſin, and fallen into the dungeon of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is now in <hi>nocte erroris;</hi> conſtrained to wander, and roaue in the darkeſome night of miſleading error. So that if we will
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Pindarus.</note> caſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor for our true ſafetie and felicitie,<pb facs="tcp:17077:28"/>we muſt let downe one in the head, and another in the ſterne of the ſhippe: that ſo here relying vpon two anchors in this heauen, we may there arriue with all ioy in that bleſſed heauen.</p>
            <p>Wherefore vnto this anchor of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, let vs ioyne the anchor of ſtedfaſt faith, and affiance. For this is that which the Apoſtle calleth
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſhield a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the firie dartes of the Diuell. This is that true <hi>Solſequium</hi> Marygold,
<note place="margin">Eph. 6.16.</note> that goes and turnes with the ſunne of righteouſneſſe Chriſt Ieſus. It is the right Salamander, that will liue, and continue in the fire without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming. And as if a man doe make him nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins and cloathes of the Salamanders haire, although they be throwne into the fire, they will not be burned and conſumed, but purged and purified: ſo will not this periſh in the fire of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, but rather with the Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der quench the fire, then be deſtroyed by the flame. Whereof wee haue a cloud of witneſſes in the ſecond of the Hebrewes: Yea, this is
<hi>anchora ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ſeruans,</hi> the anchor of the ſoule,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17077:28"/>that keepes it ſure and ſtedfaſt, from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelming and drowning in the boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ſtormes of craggie temptations, and grieuous afflictions. Wherefore bleſſed is he that truſteth in the Lord:
<note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note> for he ſhall be like the mount Sion that cannot be remoued, but remaineth for euer. And as the mountaines are about Ieruſalem, ſo will the Lord be about him for euermore.

<note place="margin">Pſal. 125.</note> 
               <hi>Aura tonet, ſonet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, maris fremat orbis &amp; orcus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tu tamen inſertos nos tibi Chriſte te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</hi> Let the winde thunder, and the waues make a noyſe: yea earth and hel fret and fume, yet thou ô bleſſed Chriſt wilt bee a wall of braſſe for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and a ſhield of proofe to keepe them ſafe that truſt in thee. He that thus caſts anchor, ſhall be as a man that is prouided of two houſes, whereof if one ſhould faile, yet the other would receiue, and keepe him. This was <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> practiſe, to caſt both anchors for his aſſurance. For praying vnto God, he calleth God his God, ſaying: Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto the voice of my prayer, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.2.</note> my king, and my <pb facs="tcp:17077:29"/>God. Hearken King, there is the firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and my God, there is the ſecond. And in the thirteenth Pſalme wherein hee ſings
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Pſalme of triumph, yet he begins the ſame with ſorrow, ſaying: <hi>Gnathana, Gnathana, Gnathana:</hi> Howe long, howe long, repeating it foure times in two verſes: but he ſtaies his griefe with the anchor of prayer, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Behold, heare me. But his prayer is mingled with faith: for he ſaith; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and heare me, O Lord my God. Heare me, there is his prayer: but heare me <hi>Iehouah Elohai,</hi> O my God; there is his faith. And this confidence, he ſets downe with the cauſe thereof, ſaying:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 13.1.2.3.4.</note> But I truſt in thy mercie, my heart ſhal reioice in thy ſaluation, and I will ſing vnto the Lord. Thus hee that began with ſorrowing, ends with ſinging, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did caſt this twofold anchor, faith, and prayer. The Cananitiſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoſe daughter was troubled with a diuel, came vnto Chriſt by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſaying: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Haue mercie vpon me O Lord, thou ſonne of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi> And the text ſaith,
<note place="margin">Matt. 15.22.28.</note> that Chriſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17077:29"/>heard her: and why? becauſe great was her faith, therefore it muſt be vnto her, as ſhe deſired. For God is <hi>cordis inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> the beholder, and ſearcher of the heart. Wherefore he ſaith not vnto her, <hi>O canis magna eſt fides tua,</hi> but <hi>O mulier, mutauit vocabulum quia mutatum vidit affectum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, c. 16.</note> O dogge, great is thy faith; but O vvoman: changing the word, becauſe ſhee had changed her faith. <hi>eudiant haec audiant, qui conſtanter orant, necrecedant. flexi inquis genua, curuaſti quidem, ſed mens tua for as vagabatur, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus intus, ſenſus foras, os loquitur, mens vſuras cogitat, O, Diabolus aſtutus: imitare imitare igitur Cananaeam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſt. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 17. in Matth.</note> Heare this, O heare this, ye that pray with vnconſtant mindes, being wearie of your worke, if you haue not too ſoone your reward, and continue ſtedfaſt. Thou ſaieſt I bende my knees: it is true; but thy minde, that runs aroauing: thy bodie indeed is in the Church, but thy vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the ſtreetes: thy mouth mutters, but thy minde, that runs after thy vſurie. O, the Diuell is craftie, that ſeekes thus to delude thee. <hi>Imitare, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitare</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17077:30"/>therefore the Cananitiſh wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; indure, and thou ſhalt be heard: adde faith vnto thy wordes, and thou ſhalt be bleſſed. <hi>Ad orationem aſſiſto, non orarem ſi non crederem, ſed ſi vere crederem, illud cor, quo Deus videtur, mundarem, genas lacrymis rigarem: iace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ad domini mei pedes, eoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fletu per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funderem, crine tergerem, haererem certo trunco crucis, nec prius amitterem quam miſerecordiam impetrarem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. in Dialog ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferi anos.</note> Marke what a learned father ſpeaketh in thy perſon. I come (ſaith he) and ſet my ſelfe vnto prayer. I would not pray vnleſſe I did beleeue I ſhould be heard. But if my faith were true, then would I cleanſe my heart which God ſo neerely marks: then would I moiſten my cheekes with my teares: then would I hang about my Maiſters feete, and all to bewaſh them with the moiſture of mine eyes, and wipe them with the cleaneſt of my haire: then would I cleaue vnto the Croſſe, and neuer leaue it, before I had obtained mercie. But now I walke while I pray, ſometimes reckening my accounts with my minde, ſometimes<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17077:30"/>hauing luſtfull deſires in my thoughts; ſeldome goeth my mind with my lips: oh where is faith? Thus did not <hi>Ionas</hi> pray: thus did not the three children call vpon God. <hi>Daniel</hi> beleeued, when he prayed in the denne; and the theefe, when he prayed on the Croſſe, he was crucified with Chriſt, and prayed in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. But we crucifie Chriſt, when we pray without beliefe: preſenting our ſelues before the king, without his ſon; before the angrie iudge, without the princes pardon, and before God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Chriſt. Like vnto a ſubiect, that hauing murthered his princes only and deare ſonne, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: with hands al beſmeared with the bloud that iſſued from the tender wounds, ſhall preſent himſelfe before the childes angrie Syre, holding vppe thoſe bloudy hands, requiring friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the father: will nor his ſonnes bloud, which ſtill preſents it ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his tender eies, incite and mooue him rather vnto furie and reuenge, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that murtherer and ſlaier of his<pb facs="tcp:17077:31"/>ſonne, then procure friendſhip and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſement for his fault? Such is the caſe of all thoſe that remaine ſtill in infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and hardneſſe of heart, and yet will offer vp their prayers vnto God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For they holde vp defiled hands, beſpotted, and beſprinkled with the bloud of Chriſt, his deare and onely ſonne; becauſe, who ſo thus remaines in his ſinne, is partaker with the Iewes in the crucifying of Chriſt, and ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his bloud,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Baſil.</note>. O therefore you that haue ſoules to ſaue, haue ſome care to bring them to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and deliuer them from hell. Bee ſorie with <hi>Peter,</hi> and repent with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Magdalen,</hi> for the folly of your liues, and the iniquitie of your daies, which you haue foreſpent in ſinne and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. <hi>Tunc enim incipit medicina vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae proficere, vbi in animo contribulato mens maerorem exercet:</hi> For then begins the Phyſicke of grace to amend our ſicke ſoules, when the minde of man draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth ſorrowe and griefe from a troubled ſpirit in deteſtation of his ſins,<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17077:31"/>that haue ſo highly diſhonoured his mercifull God. <hi>Dauid</hi> in remembrance of his ſinnes waſhed his bed with the drops of his eies, and ſaith: that his teares were his bread, both day and night. And God ſet the letter
<hi>Tau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 9.4.</note> as a marke of ſaluation, vpon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads of them that did mourne for the abhominations of Ieruſalem. And <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> writeth thus of himſelfe. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baui animam meam, &amp; impatientem por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari à me, at vbi eam ponerem non inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebam: non in amaenis nemoribus, non in ludis at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> canticis, non in locis ſuaue olen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. 4. lib. of his conf.</note> I tried and ſearched my ſoule, and found it to be heauie, and full of impatience; but where I ſhould eaſe me of this loade, or finde releaſe for my burthen, I could not tell. I went to the pleaſant woods, but there I found it not. I ſought for muſicke, and ſport, but there it was not. I had recourſe to the ſweete ſmelling gardens, but here I found no eaſe. I feaſted, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe in dainties: ſometimes I betooke me to my chamber for wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, ſometimes to my Librarie for <pb facs="tcp:17077:32"/>weariſomneſſe: but neither in meates, nor drinckes, in bookes, nor beds, did my ſoule take reſt or comfort. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted all thinges, that were not that thing which it ſelfe deſired, and that was God. Each thing was odious vnto it, if it were not a ſob for ſinning, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alone it found ſome reſt. As in a healthfull bath, that waſhed it of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, and made it freſh for the iourney of ſaluation. O remember the country Metaphore of the Pſalmiſt: He that ſowes in teares, ſhall reape in ioy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> This world is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, that the repaying world: this for worke, that for paiment: this for triall, that for comfort. And if thou ſhalt with patience vndergoe the fire of triall in this world; thou ſhalt with comfort, receiue the ioy of perfection in the world to come. If in this world, thou ſhalt work out thy ſaluation with feare, and trembling; thou ſhalt receiue Gods bleſſed paiment (a crowne of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall happineſſe) in the worlde to<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17077:32"/>come. If in this worlde, thou ſhalt cleanſe thy pathes, and moiſten thy ſoule with the teares of repentance; thou ſhalt receiue a paradiſe of ioyes in the world to come. For then God will heare our prayers; when wordes and workes, hands and hearts, faith &amp; repentance ſhal kiſſe each other. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when the tempeſt of perſecution ſhall inuade vs, and the ſtormes of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſhall riſe againſt vs, and we caſt the anchor of prayer, either in this houſe, or in anie other: let vs take heed that we come in feare and faith; and not in toying and tatling, leaſt we make
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the houſe of prayer, a place of prating. For <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the Angels ſtand by vs to take our words, and God is preſent to knowe our hearts. But if our prayers be made in faith, we ſhall no ſooner aske, but God will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: behold, I am preſent to grant thy requeſt. Out of this that hath been ſpoken, there ariſeth eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally two concluſions. Firſt, that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is a neceſſarie anchor for this ſhippe.<pb facs="tcp:17077:33"/>The ſecond, that prayer without faith, is not a ſufficient anchor to ſtay ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie a ſhippe, in ſo troubleſome a ſea. Againſt the neceſſitie of the firſt, the Epicures, Stoickes, and Egyptian Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers diſpute, after this manner. If this be ſo neceſſarie an anchor, for ſo burthenſome a ſhippe; then it muſt ſerue either <hi>vt intimemus ei à quo peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus illud quo indigemus:</hi> or <hi>vt per oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem flectatur animus eius qui oratur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Th Aquin. lib. contra ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, c. 96.</note> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that we might ſignifie vnto him of whom we deſire a thing, what we doe want: or els that we might mooue, or by our prayers bend his mind to grant our requeſts. But neither of theſe is needfull. For the firſt: God ſtandeth not in need of our inſtructions, neither doth he want vs to admoniſh him of our neceſſities: but knowes
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> what we haue neede of before we aske.
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.32.</note> As Chriſt ſpeaketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his diſciples, ſaying; that your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father knoweth that ye want all theſe things. And for the ſecond <hi>Ain Iehouah lo ſhanithi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Malach. 3.</note> I am the Lorde, I change not: with whom there is no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riableneſſe,<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17077:33"/>nor ſhaddowe of turning.
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> But <hi>vt immutabilis natura ſic voluntas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. 5. moral. nat. 18.</note> as his nature is vnchangeable, ſo his will cannot be altered. Vnto the firſt we may giue this manifold anſwere. Firſt, with <hi>Hierome, nos non ſumus narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores, ſed oratores:</hi> wee are not tellers, but ſutors. For it is one thing to declare a thing to him that knowes it not, and another thing to require a thing of him that alreadie knoweth it. Secondly, we anſwere with
<hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that it is <hi>elenchus cauſae,</hi> a falſe cauſe; and therefore denie the argument. For albeit God knowes how to giue good things vnto his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yet he commaundeth vs to aske, ſeeke, and knocke, that by this meanes, <hi>exerceri in orationibus deſiderium noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. 121.</note> our deſires might be exerciſed in our prayers, whereby we may receiue thoſe things, which he hath prepared to giue vs. And laſtly, the neceſſitie of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſiſts not, in that we ſhould open to God our wants; but that we might be put in minde, whither to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in our extremities. And for the ſecond, we may anſwere, that it is the <pb facs="tcp:17077:34"/>felfeſame fallacion. For albeit God be ſaid to change; yet that is but by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphore
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: becauſe it is not
<hi>mutat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Dei,</hi> but
<hi>rei:</hi> not <hi>conſilij,</hi> but <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peris:</hi> not
<hi>affectus,</hi> but <hi>effectus:</hi> not God, but the thing is chaunged: not Gods councell, but Gods worke: not his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but effect. Yet this is not the end of our prayers to make God changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but that by praying we might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thoſe things in time, which God hath decreed to beſtow vpon vs from all eternitie. For prayer is not <hi>ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutandam prouidentiam ſed ad insplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam:</hi> not to alter Gods minde, but to fulfill his prouidence: ſeeing that thoſe things <hi>quae ſancti viri orando efficiunt, ita praedeſtinata ſunt vt precibus illa obtineant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. 16.18.</note> which holy men haue accompliſhed by praying, were ſo ordained, as they ſhould obtaine them by their prayers. As when God had promiſed <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> that in <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſeede ſhould be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; yet God gaue vnto <hi>Iſaac</hi> a barren wife, wherfore <hi>Iſaac</hi> praied for his wife <hi>Rebeccha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.</note> and the text ſaith; that the Lord was intreated of him, and his<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17077:34"/>wife <hi>Rebeccha</hi> conceaued. This then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines a firme anchor for this ſhippe, contrarie to the opinion of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Philoſophers, and the followers of
<hi>Pelagian:</hi> yea contrarie to the common Chriſtian, who though he profeſſe chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie in word; yet he practiſeth Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagianiſme in his works. For doe not our liues practiſe that which <hi>Pelagian</hi> profeſſed: namely, that we thinke prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is but needleſſe? Yea, was not this an eſpecial hereſie of the Pelagian, <hi>quod deſtrueret orationes eccleſiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. 106.</note> that he went about to deſtroye the prayers of the Church? And is not this our profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by our practiſe, who ſo ſeldome frequent the Church, and ſeeke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede by couert meanes to ouerthrow religion?</p>
            <p>Againſt the ſecond concluſion, the aduerſarie obiecteth after this order: If faith be ſo neceſſarie a companion for prayer, as without it, prayer can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anchor this heauie ſhippe: then how commeth it to paſſe, that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull mans prayers, are oftentimes heard, and fulfilled; but the godly and<pb facs="tcp:17077:35"/>faithfull mans requeſts, are often deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and reiected.</p>
            <p>Touching the firſt, learned writers ſufficiently reſolue thee after this ſort: Firſt, God heares our prayers, <hi>vel ad iuſtitiam, vel ad miſerecordiam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. 37. in Ioh.</note> either for iuſtice, or for mercie. And for both theſe endes, he oftentimes receiues the prayers of the wicked. Firſt according to his mercie, <hi>vt eos beneficijs ad amorem ſuam alliciat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. li. 1. cap. 4. de bonis oper.</note> that he might win them vnto him by his benefits: and thus he heard the praiers of the Niniuites, not according to his iuſtice, but according to his mercie. Secondly, according to his iuſtice; and thus he heard the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, requiring fleſh in the deſart. But while the meate was in their mouthes,
<note place="margin">Numb. 11.</note> the wrath of the Lord came vpon them and deſtroyed them: <hi>Metuendum ergo eſt</hi> (ſaith Saint
<hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>ne id hoc poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet non dare propitius, det iratus.</hi> O ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs take heede, leaſt that which God cannot beſtow vpon vs as a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God, he repayeth as an angrie Iudge.</p>
            <p>A ſecond cauſe why God heareth<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17077:35"/>the prayers of the wicked, is <hi>populi ſui cauſa:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sadel in vera pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione.</note> for the more comfort of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued people. Seeing that God is ſo mercifull vnto thoſe which are wicked, and his enemies; how muſt they but needes be perſuaded, that he will bee much more fauourable vnto the godly and his friends?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the wicked are not heard, <hi>ex ſpeciali gratia, ſed ex communi miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caluin. lib. 3. confeſſ. ca. 20. ſect.
15.</note> not that God is well pleaſed at their prayers, but to ſet out his mercie by this circumſtance: For that euen vnto vnbeleeuers their prayers are not denied, the more to pricke forward thoſe which ſerue God, to be carefull at all times to pray vnto him, ſeeing that the verie wicked and prophane, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes obtaine their petitions.</p>
            <p>And as concerning the ſecond part of their obiection; It is true, that the Lord at all times grants not the prayers of the godly. For
<hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the meſſenger of Satan,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.2</note> yea hee beſought the Lord thriſe, that it might depart from him; but hee was not heard. And the reaſon was (as <pb facs="tcp:17077:36"/>ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>quia non expedie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. 121.</note> Firſt, leaſt that he ſhould be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of meaſure: and ſecondly, that Gods power might be made manifeſt through weakeneſſe. And yet he was heard; and not heard, becauſe there is a double kinde of hearing; one <hi>ad vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem,</hi> another <hi>ad ſalutem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Iohn.</note> one to anſwere our wils, and another for our good. So likewiſe there is a twofolde kinde of deliuerance: one <hi>ex preſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus periculis:</hi> one for preſent dangers, and calamities; as he deliuered <hi>Dauid</hi> from <hi>Saul, Daniel</hi> from the Princes, the Iſraelites from <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that his Church might haue ſome outward teſtimonies of his loue and fauour. And this is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a corporall deliuerance. There is another deliuerance, which is called a ſpirituall deliuerance: When God ſo ſtrengtheneth the harts of his ſeruants, as they patiently abide the afflictions of their foes. And thus God deliuereth them, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Baſil.</note>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not ſo much by freeing them from their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, as by ſtrengthening them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17077:36"/>perſecutions.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.17.</note> For the righteous crie, and the Lord heareth them, and deliuereth them out of all their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. He heareth them for their good, though not for their delight; and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth them ſpiritually, albeit not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally. Yet the time will come, when they likewiſe ſhall be deliuered: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when he ſhall take them from this miſerable life, to euerlaſting ioyes. Wherefore, aske (ſaith Chriſt)
<note place="margin">Iohn, 16.</note> in my name, and ye ſhall receiue, but ye ſhall receiue <hi>quando debetis accipere, quaedam enim non negantur, ſed vt congruo dentur tempore differuntur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. 102.</note> when ye ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them. For ſome things are not ſimply denied, but conditionally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, to their proper time and place. Let vs therfore aske (ſaith Saint
<hi>Iames</hi>)
<note place="margin">Iames, 1.</note> in faith, nothing doubting: and then (ſaith Chriſt)
<note place="margin">Matt. 21.</note> whatſoeuer ye ſhall aske, ye ſhall receiue. For prayer thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled; <hi>Eſt Dei columba quae ramum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuae apportat, dum pacem hominibus impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trat:</hi> Is Gods Doue, which carrieth the Oliue branche in token of peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and man. Yea the holy<pb facs="tcp:17077:37"/>Ghoſt the true Doue, that firſt perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to pray, ſhall aſſure vs of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, becauſe God is well pleaſed with vs. But that this may pleaſe God, and profit vs; we muſt vnderſtand, that there is a threefolde kinde of prayer: <hi>mentalis, vocalis, vitalis.</hi> The firſt is, when we pray with vnderſtanding: the ſecond with our lips; and the laſt with our liues. All which, if conioyned in brotherhood, they make a ſtrong cord to binde Gods bleſſings vnto vs: but if diſioined in hatred, they ſeperate Gods fauour from vs. For he that ſaith well, but liueth ill; <hi>non inuocat Deum patrem, ſed diabolum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Nicen. 2. orat. de dominica orat.</note> maketh not God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but calleth on the Diuell, when he prayeth our Father. And ſaith the wiſe man: He that ſtoppeth his eares leaſt he ſhould heare the law, ſhall be abhominable. Wherfore (ſaith the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) If thou looſe the bands of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, let the oppreſſed goe free, breake thy bread vnto the hungrie, lodge the wanderer, and couer the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked:
<note place="margin">Eſay, 58.6.7.8.9.</note> then ſhalt thou call, and the Lord ſhall anſwere; thou ſhalt crie, and hee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17077:37"/>ſhall ſay, here I am. And thus much for the firſt part, which are the anchors that we muſt caſt; and they are two: Prayer, and Affiance.</p>
            <p>Now ſolloweth the ſecond, and that is the ſhippe that muſt bee ſtaied by theſe anchors: namely, a loaden ſhippe, called here
<hi>Iehabcha,</hi> thy burthen. For man, miſerable man, is in this world
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lus,</hi> a loaden and burthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned porter: yea
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, verie heauie loaden;
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.29</note> hauing one loade,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <note place="margin">Nazinze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>Sickneſſe, pouertie, children, oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, death, hatred, men, beaſts, ſea, land, griefes, and troubles, all miſeries for this life, and burthens for this loade. For
<hi>vita eſt poena,</hi> yea <hi>totae poena,</hi> I <hi>poena &amp; miſeria:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. 21.</note> life is a puniſhment, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither paine and puniſhment, I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but paine and miſerie.
<note place="margin">Greg. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. 11.</note> Being ſometimes
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, other times
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23.24. &amp;c.</note> now in labour, then in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: now in priſon, then in whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: ſometimes ſtoned, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſuffering ſhipwracke: ſometimes<pb facs="tcp:17077:38"/>in perils by waters, and ſometimes in perils by theeues: otherwhiles in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by our nation, and otherwhiles in danger by ſtrangers. Now in the city, and then againe in the wildernes: ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſubiect to wearineſſe, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to painfulneſſe: verie often ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to hunger, to thirſt, to watching, to faſting, to colde, to nakedneſſe, to death, &amp;c. Rightly compared vnto the ſea, yea to <hi>Mare Aegaeum,</hi> where the <hi>venti, auguſtiae, Caribdis, ſtagna, Syrtes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſto.</note> windes, waues, rockes, and ſands, verie hard to be ſayled. And by <hi>Iob</hi> called a warfare, where is nothing but hazard, and trouble; feare, and diſtreſſe. For in this life there is <hi>timor, tremor, fames, ſitis, calor, frigor, languor, dolor:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> feare, trembling, hunger, thirſt, heate, colde, faintneſſe, and ſorrow.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Menander.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p> O miſerable mortals, how are ye turned, and toſſed, torne, and tormoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with miſchiefes and miſeries? your life is ſhort of continuance, yet full of miſerie.
<note place="margin">Iob. 14.1.</note> A wonderfull thing, <hi>breuem appellat vitam;</hi> but <hi>miſerias, quibus in hac<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17077:38"/>vita afficimur multas.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregorie.</note> The holy man cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth life ſhort, yet the miſeries of this life hee tearmeth manie: but ſeeme it neuer ſo ſtrange, true it is that our life is ſhort, and our miſeries verie manie.
<note place="margin">Wiſdom. 5.</note> For man is compared to the paſſing of a ſhippe, to the flying of an arrow to <hi>erreg:</hi> the little ſhippe that runneth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the weauers ſhittle.
<note place="margin">Iob. 7.2.</note> And verie well ſaid to be ſwifter. For <hi>tela tordita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem profectus habet,</hi> but <hi>vita moram de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus non habet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregorie.</note> The ſhittle hath ſome ſlownes in going forwards, but mans life hath neither ſlackneſſe nor delay, in going vnto death.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <note place="margin">Anacreon.</note>
                  </l>
               </q> Being compared (by the Poet) vnto a whirligig, and proued by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. For being now merrie drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of wine, he was ſodainly choaked with the grape, and died.
<note place="margin">Cron. 1.29.</note> Yea it is compared vnto a ſhaddow,
<note place="margin">Iob. 14.2.</note> and phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Iob, yibrach catzel:</hi> it flieth or vaniſheth like a ſhaddowe: <hi>fugit, non mouetur,</hi> to note <hi>breuitatem:</hi> but <hi>ſicut vmbra,</hi> to note
<hi>inconſtantiam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eucherius.</note> It flies not ſoftly moues, to note the ſhortnes:<pb facs="tcp:17077:39"/>but it flieth as a ſhaddow, and not as a body, to note the inſtableneſſe. For there is nothing more vaine, more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, more ſwift, and more fraile, then mans life, howbeit full of miſerie. For here,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </q>Griefe, and life, are like Hypocrites, twins, kinsfolke, and brethren. Here <hi>febres necant, dolores opprimunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſolil. 2</note> ſickneſſe killeth, ſorrow oppreſſeth, hunger fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſheth, thirſt diſpatcheth, water choa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, the halter ſtrangleth, the fire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth, the beaſt deuoureth, the ſword ſlaieth, and poyſon corrupteth. Thus is life a fraile life, a flitting life: a life, the more it lengtheneth, the ſhorter it wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; the more it increaſeth, the nigher it draweth vnto death. A life tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, deceitfull, miſerable, and repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with change and mutabilitie: ſo that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<note place="margin">Atheneus.</note> it is the beſt not at all to be borne, and if a man be borne, it is the ſafeſt to die ſoone. This maketh him begin his daies with teares.
<note place="margin">Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius</note> 
               <hi>Maſculus recenter natus clamat A, fomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na E, dicentes E vel A, quotquot naſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17077:39"/>ab Euah.</hi> The man child commeth into the worlde crying A, and the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male E, all ſounding out E or A, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer come of the loynes of
<hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Euah.</hi> A condition exceeding in miſerie, the eſtate of all other creatures; becauſe no creature elſe beginneth his daies with woe and weeping but only man, as the Naturaliſts could well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue.
<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 7. Tertul. Auguſt.</note> For man is <hi>augur in commodorum, &amp; propheta ſuae calamitatis:</hi> a Prophet and foreteller of his owne calamitie, and diſcommoditie: who no ſooner borne, but fals to ſhedde his teares, as witneſſes of his inſuing miſerie. <hi>O ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio flebilis, O infoelix, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. de ſpec. poenit.</note> O lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, wofull, and vnhappy generation, whoſe father is care, whoſe mother is ſhame, whoſe ſiſter is vncleaneneſſe, whoſe nurſe is folly, and miſguiding falſehood; whoſe wife is pleaſure, and beſotting ſinne; whoſe childe &amp; heire, is paine, and bitter puniſhment: called by the wiſe man, miſerable earth; and by the Apoſtle, veſſell of diſhonour, begotten in vncleannes, liuing in wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe, and dying in diſtreſſe.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 17. Rom. 9. Pſal. 51.5. Iob.
14.</note> A<pb facs="tcp:17077:40"/>rotten carkaſſe, meate for wormes, and matter for euerburning fire.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 14. Eſay. 51. Matth. 25.</note> 
               <hi>O memen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to homo quis es, vbi es, &amp; vbi non es:</hi> call call O man vnto thy remembraunce, what thou art, where thou art, and where thou art not: Thou art the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of vanitie, not by creation, but by default; thou art in the vaile of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, and valley of deſtruction.
<note place="margin">Beda: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortat. cap. 119.</note> O view and conſider thy ſelfe inſtantly, and bewaile thy lamentable caſe inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly.</p>
            <p>This ſearch conſiſteth in theſe three things. Firſt, why man is thus burthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Secondly, what brought this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vpon man. Thirdly, what is the eaſe, or ſoueraigne remedie for this burthen.</p>
            <p>Firſt, why is man thus burthened? <hi>Gregorie</hi> anſwereth:
<hi>ne viam pro patria diligamus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>l. 23. c. 22</note> leaſt delighting too much in the way, we preferre it before our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly countrey. For this life is but the way, wherein we walke vnto our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which is heauen. Now it is the cuſtome of many trauellers, when they beholde ſome faire and pleaſant places,<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17077:40"/>obiected vnto them in their iourney, to ſlacke their pace, and walke out of their way; the rather to delight, and beſot themſelues with this obiect. So might it happen vnto the Chriſtian traueller, were not this burthen heauie vpon his backe; the waight whereof, weans him from the delight of this world. For the world is like vnto
<hi>Salomons</hi> harlot, that layeth open her breaſts to intiſe trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and ſtrangers. The two dugges whereof, are profit and pleaſure. With the firſt, ſhe deales like <hi>Hypomanes</hi> to <hi>Atalanta;</hi> who being to runne a race for a kingdome and victorie, <hi>Hypomanes</hi> caſting a ball of golde on this ſide, and another on that ſide; ſo beſotted <hi>Ata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanta</hi> with the deſire of them, as ſhee running out of the way to enioye the golde, loſt the goale, the victorie, and the priſe. So doth the world miſleade the greedie, the couetous, and the gold-deſiring Merchant. With the ſecond, ſhee deales like
<hi>Cyrces;</hi> who alluring <hi>Gryllus</hi> to taſte of her drugges, made him ſo drunken with the pleaſure ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as he neither remembred the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<pb facs="tcp:17077:41"/>of his nature, nor deſired the ſight of his countrey. So deales the world with the delicious, drunken, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable worldling. Being ſometimes compared vnto birdlime: the Diuel the fowler, who wrappes the worldling, as the birde is wrapped in the lime. And ſometimes vnto a Net: profit, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure are the baite; vnto which, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy worldling no ſooner ſtoupes, but he is taken in the net. Or he may be compared vnto a man, that running apace, falleth ere he be aware into a pit; and as he is falling, catcheth hold on a ſhrubbe; whereby getting a little hold for his feete, beginneth to looke about him;
<note place="margin">Damaſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</note> where behinde him, he ſeeth two Mice gnawing at the root of the ſhrub: beneath in the bottome, he beholdeth a firie Dragon gaping to deuoure him: at his feete, he perceiueth foure Aſpes peeping out to ſting him: aboue him, he deſcrieth ſome few droppes of allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hony ſprinkled vpon the ſhrubbe, wherewith hee being enamoured and beſotted, not minding the reſt of his miſeries, looſeth his holde, to take and<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17077:41"/>taſte the hony; but falleth downe, and is deſtroyed. The pit here ſignifieth the world, whereinto man is entred: the ſhrub repreſenteth this life, which man awhile enioyeth: the two Mice are the night and the day, which catech and gnaweth vpon the life: the foure Aſpes note our foure humours, which moleſt and conſume vs: the firie Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon is the Diuell, which gapeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs: the hony is the delight and pleaſure of this world, which ſinfull man beholding, is enamoured with it, and being enamoured, catcheth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy it, and catching, forſaketh his hold, and falleth into the pit of deſtruction, there for euer deuoured of the Diuell. Yea <hi>iter vitae noſtrae,</hi> is <hi>vt ſi ſtagnum eſſet tranſiundum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cui pons impoſitus eſſet ita an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus, vt vix harere illi pes poſſet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſiodorus.</note> Man in this lifes iourney, hath to paſſe (as it were) a great lake, or poole, whereouer a verie narrow bridge was placed for his paſſage, yea ſo narrowe, as he can ſcarcely finde any footing on it; vnder which bridge, there be firi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Serpents, venemous Crocadiles, and deuouring beaſts,
<pb facs="tcp:17077:42"/>who are readie to receiue him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing to deſtroy him, if he chance to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lippe, and fall off from the bridge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And yet on both ſides of the poole, there are pleaſant fieldes, delightfull gardens, and moſt artificiall buildings, which might bring great delight, and admiration to the beholders. What now doe we thinke is beſt for this man? Dare he caſt his eies vpon this pleaſure? Wiſedome teacheth vs, no: for by that meanes, enioying a minde of pleaſure with his eyes, he might perhaps fal, and ſuſtaine loſſe and deſtruction for euer, and euer. And ſhall wiſedome teach vs this pollicie for our bodies, and ſhall not the heauenly wiſedome perſuade vs, to be more careful for ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die? He will not caſt his eies on thoſe pleaſures, leaſt he ſuſtaine a temporall puniſhment; and ſhall we ſet our affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon wordly delights, for euer after to endure eternall deſtruction? O rather, let vs make a league with our eies, leaſt we behold vanitie, and watch our waies, leaſt we be ouertaken with folly; and ſo forget the ſtreight bridge <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17077:42"/>which here we are to paſſe, and ſlipping with our burthens vpon our backes, be preſſed downe to the bottome of hell. <hi>Baſill</hi> telleth vs, that there be but two waies for euery man to walke in, in this life: the one whereof he muſt needes chuſe. The firſt is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the ſecond <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the firſt is the way that leadeth vnto vertue; and the ſecond, the way that leadeth vnto vice. In the firſt way walketh the good and godly man: in the ſecond, the ſinner and vniuſt. The firſt way
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> the firſt way ſheweth all the good we muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be performed vnto vs in the life to come. The ſecond ſheweth all the benefit we can hope for, to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this preſent world. The firſt, as it promiſeth much good for to come, ſo it aſſureth vs of much labour to bee vndergone. But <hi>mundus iſte multa de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectabilia oſtendit hominibus, ſed ad ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſto.</note> The ſecond, which is the way of the world, it ſheweth and promiſeth manie pleaſures, and delights togither with much eaſe, but all to ſeduce the<pb facs="tcp:17077:43"/>careleſſe worldling. Euen as a couſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fellow, vnderſtranding a childe an orphane to be poſſeſſed of his patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and ſubſtance; inuiteth him now to this feaſt, &amp; then againe to that ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet (as the harlots dealt with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall childe) while he bereaues, and deceiues him of all his goods and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: So dealeth the diuel with man, he offereth him pleaſure, but to deſtroy his ſoule: earthly profit, but to bereaue him of his heauenly treaſure. For <hi>fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus mundi ruina eſt, ad hoc floret, vt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat, ad hoc blanditur vt decipiat, ad hoc germinat, vt quodcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> germinauerit cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus conſumatur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. mor. 7. cap. 21.</note> For the fruit which the world can giue, is but downfals, and the ende for which it beſtoweth his fruit, &amp; goods vpon vs, is but to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, beguile, deceiue, and deſtroy vs. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<note place="margin">Baſilius.</note> Bleſſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that man which is not taken with the baite of worldly pleaſure, nor turned into the way of deſtruction. Bleſſed is he that hath not walked in the way of ſinners,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.5.</note> yea ten times bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17077:43"/>is he, whoſe burthen is borne here with patience, and ſo tied vnto the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor of faith, as it weanes him from this preſent world, and winnes him to breath onely for the world to come. Then <hi>medicina eſt, non poena:</hi> then is this burthen phyſicke to ſalue our ſoules, and not continuall paine to torment them.
<note place="margin">Aug. in pſal. 103.</note>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſto.</note> Then is this burthen
<hi>pedagogus</hi> a ſchoolemaſter, to traine vs in true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and teach vs in the way of life. Which who ſo wanteth, may rightly ſuſpect himſelfe, ſeeing the Lord (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the Angell of Laodicea) ſaith:
<note place="margin">Reu. 3.19.</note> Whom I loue, I rebuke. Chriſt muſt paſſe by the croſſe, vnto glorie: and all that will liue godly, muſt endure croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Wherfore (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſe)
<note place="margin">Prou. 3.1.</note> My ſonne, refuſe not the chaſtening of the Lord, neither be grieued at his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: for the Lord correcteth him whom he loueth, euen as the father the childe in whom he delighteth. Is God a Father then when he correcteth? and ſheweth he moſt loue when he beates?
<note place="margin">Aug. in pſal. 91.</note> 
               <hi>Quid ſi te flagellat, modo propterea, quia tibi non ſeruat ignem ſempeternum? Quid
<pb facs="tcp:17077:44"/>ſi illum dimittit quia auditurus eſt, Ite in ignem.</hi> What if God thy Father whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, and ſcourgeth thee in this life; is it not becauſe he prepareth thee for a better inheritance, and not preſerues thee for euerlaſting fire? And what if he letteth him or another man go ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free, and eſcape; is it not becauſe he giues him his portion of pleaſure, and profit in this life, and ſhall therefore heare that fearefull ſentence, Go yee curſed into euerlaſting fire? O then bleſſed is he
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Baſil</note> which ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth off the world, and the pleaſure therof: neither putteth any confidence in the things of this life; but placeth all his hope, truſt, and affiance vpon God alone, his maker, Sauiour, and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. And ſo much for the firſt point: why man is thus burthened.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, what brought this burthen vpon man: and that is in a word: Sinne. For <hi>Adam</hi> ſinning, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the earth to be curſed, loſt his dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie ouer the creatures, became ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſickneſſe and death, and made himſelfe, and his poſteritie, obnoxious
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17077:44"/>vnto deſtruction. For this cauſe, ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt vnto the man that had lien ſicke eight and thirtie yeares; Behold thou art made whole, ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing happen vnto thee: noting unto vs, that ſickneſſe is laid vpon vs for our ſinne. For this cauſe labour and paine was laid vpon <hi>Adam</hi> and his poſteritie, and moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous paines in childbirth vpon the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> For this cauſe hath God added to this burthen, fearefulneſſe, conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, burning agues, enemies: yea (ſaith God) if ye will not obey me, then will I puniſh you ſeauen times more, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your ſins;
<note place="margin">Leuit. 26.16.17.18.</note> namely, with weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, drought, barrenneſſe, and famine. And if ye will not yet obey me (ſaith God) I will bring ſeauen times more plagues vpon you according to your ſinnes; as the ſword, plagues, wilde beaſts. And if ye will not yet obey me, then wil I chaſtiſe you ſeauen times more, according to your ſinnes; you ſhall eate the fleſh of your ſonnes and daughters, your places ſhall be deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and your carkaſſes ſhall be burnt, <pb facs="tcp:17077:45"/>your Cities ſhall be deſolate, your ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie brought to nought, and your land turned into a wilderneſſe. I will ſcatter you among the Heathen, and draw a ſword after you: I will ſend a faintneſſe into your hearts, and the ſound of a leafe ſhaken, ſhall chaſe you: you ſhall fall, and no man ſhall purſue you: ye ſhall periſh, and your enemies ſhall eate you vp. Thus the Lord ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in that Chapter, from ſeauen times to ſeauen times, threatning moſt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full puniſhments, and that by a thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring gradation, and all for ſinne.
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.14.</note> For this cauſe is added vnto this burthen, horror of conſcience, madneſſe, blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and aſtoniſhment of heart: yea what is not added to this burthen, and all for ſinne? If thou wilt not keepe my commandements (ſaith God) then all theſe curſes ſhall come vpon thee, and ouertake thee: Curſed ſhalt thou be in the towne, and curſed alſo in the field; curſed ſhall thy basket be, and thy dough curſed: curſed ſhall be the fruite of thy land, the increaſe of thy kine, and the flockes of thy ſheepe:<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17077:45"/>curſed ſhalt thou be, when thou comeſt in, and curſed when thou goeſt out. The Lord ſhall ſend vpon thee curſing trouble, and ſhame, in all which thou ſetteſt thy hand vnto, vntill thou bee deſtroyed; and periſheſt quickly becauſe of the wickedneſſe of thy workes. And if for all this thou wilt not keepe his law, then will hee make thy plagues wonderfull, &amp; the plagues of thy ſeede. He will bring vpon thee all the diſeaſes of Egipt, and euery ſickneſſe, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery plague will he heape vpon thee: with many other fearefull threatninges foreſpoken in the booke of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
<note place="margin">Theſialonians 1.1. cap. 8.9.</note> Yea for this cauſe doth he adde to this burden euerlaſting deſtruction when the Lord Ieſus ſhal ſhew himſelfe from heauen, with his mightie Angels, in flaming fire, rendering vengance vnto them that do not knovv God, and will obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall be puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition, from the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Lord, and from the glorie of his power. <hi>Dam infelix homo a domino rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, à carne moleſtias, à monte auguſtias,<pb facs="tcp:17077:46"/>vndi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> premitur anxietatibus, vrgetur infirmitatibus, polluitur paſſionibus, graue pondus ſeipſum portat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. 8. mora. Cap. 21.</note> while man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie man, recoyles from the ſeruice of his God, he is moleſted by the fleſh, vexed by the ſpirit: yea both body and ſoule are nothing but a burden to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, too heauy to bee borne, yet fooliſh ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hoped by diſobeying God, to haue bettered himſelfe. But <hi>anima verſa &amp; reuerſa in tergum, ventrem, latera ſentit, quodomnia ſunt dura.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Confeſſ. 6.</note> Turning and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from backe to belly, ſearching the heart; the ſides, the intrales, found all out of quiet and nothing to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. And why?
<note place="margin">Baſilius.</note> As ſmoake dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth away the Bee from the hiue, ſo ſurfeiting, drunkenneſſe and other ſinnes, chaſe away Gods ſpirit, and all other ſpirituall graces, which are the onely comfortes of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſephus</hi> reporterh that a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Hieruſalem was beſeiged by <hi>Titus,</hi> the doores of the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie ſuddenly opened, and a great noyſe was hearde ſaying: <hi>migre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17077:46"/>hinc:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſephus. lib. 7.12.</note> let vs go hence. To note vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs that neither God nor his Angels will make aboad, where ſin hath once obtained dominion, and prehemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For <hi>anima peccatoris magis fet at cor am deo, quam putridum carnis cadauer.</hi> The ſinfull ſoule ſmelleth more filthily in the noſtrels of God, then the rankeſt carrion in the noſe of man. O therefore beware of the inticements of Sathan, the allurements of ſinne, and ſtoupe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to their lure nor offer to taſt vpon their baite, <hi>porris ac coepis ſimile eſt pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. 11. cap. 16.</note> ſin is like vnto garlicke and oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that breeds loathing vnto the ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and weeping vnto the eater. I am (ſaith the penitent ſoule) in the tauerne of vanitie, and I taſted the cup of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: <hi>hauſtum felicitatis obtulit:</hi> but <hi>poculum mortis propinauit.</hi> there was <hi>mel in ore,</hi> but
<hi>it fel in ventre, appa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uit in palato vinum,</hi> but <hi>in ſtomacho experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae abſinthium, &amp; vera mors in olla.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beda ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor. 13.5.</note> There was offered me a cup of felicitie, but ſin began vnto me in a cup of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, it ſeemed in my mouth to be as ſweete as honie, but I felt it in my bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<pb facs="tcp:17077:47"/>as bitter as gall: I hoped to haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a cup of delight, but behold in the bottome there were drugges of loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome confuſion. It ſeemed in my pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to be pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wine: But I proued it in my ſtomach to bebitter wormwood, and to ſay the truth there was eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death it ſelfe in the cup. Neither are wee to expect any thing elſe of ſin, then death ſeeing the greateſt reward that ſin can afforde vs is death and deſtruction.
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.21.</note> vAnd thus much for the ſecond point.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the third, which is the remedy againſt this burden, &amp; that is twofold the one to giue a remoue vnto ſin, and the other, to caſt they bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vpon the Lord. For the firſt. Sinne is like a leauen, that will leauen the whole lumpe, like a poyſon that will corrupt the whole body: like a plague that will infect the whole houſe, yea it is
<hi>ignis ardens,</hi> a burning fire that will conſume the whole Cittie. Now if we would not haue the whole lumpe to be leauened, we muſt take away the leaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor the body to be corrupted, we muſt ſend away the poyſon, nor the houſe to<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17077:47"/>be infected, we muſt chaſe away the plague, nor the Citie to be burned we muſt quench out the fire, nor the man to be deſtroyed we muſtremoue the ſin. For <hi>quantum peccandi materiam ſuſtule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, tantum extinguetur: quantum adie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceris, tantum accendetur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Heremita.</note> The more thou ſhalt detract from the matter of ſin, the more thou ſhalt diminiſh it. ſeeing the cauſe being
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aken away the effect likewiſe will decay. For as <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otimus,</hi> if he had obeyed the Phiſicians counſell in abſtaining from vnclea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, he had ſaued his eyes:
<note place="margin">Ambroſius in Luke.</note> ſo man had ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued both body and ſoule, had he abſtai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned from ſin and iniquitie. Sin is like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto a flegmaticke ſtomacke: <hi>ſi euomu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, releuatur:</hi> If it vomites it is eaſed, becauſe it diſgorgeth that which moſt heauily did moleſt it. The vomite of our ſinfull ſoules is confeſſion of our ſinnes vnto God, and the beſt way to keepe our ſoules from corrupting, is to vſe, the diet of abſtinene from ſin and iniquitie. Thus much was inſinuated by
<hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt vnto the Iewes, and by Chriſt vnto his diſciples, willing them<pb facs="tcp:17077:48"/>to preach repentance, for the kingdome of God is at hand. Now then ſeeing thou haſt found the way to remoue thy ſin, and obtained of thy Phiſician a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to purge thy iniquitie, which is repentance: <hi>cur ceſſas aggredi quod ſcias mederi tibi? cervus ſagitta tranſfix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſcit ſibi Dictamno mederi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertulliaus lib depaenitent.</note> why doeſt thou delay to aſſay that which will be thy cure? The Hart no ſooner peirced with the dart, but preſently runnes to heale her ſelfe with Dittinie: The ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low if her young ones chance to haue their ſight put out by any miſchance flies, preſently for ſwallowort to redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me their ſight. The Lord counſelleth thee, to ſeeke for him while he may be founde. For it may be <hi>qui tempus ſene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctutis expectat ad poenitendum, dum ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret miſerecordiam inveniet iudicium<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregorius</note> That he who boaſteth of his repentance vntil the time of age, or the day of death, inſtead of mercie, may finde iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wherefore
<note place="margin">Chryſost.</note> 
               <hi>ſeminemus dum eſt tempus, vt metamus, nauigemus dum mare nauigari poteſt, antequam ſit hyemps, quando magnus ille, &amp; tremendus dies aduenerit non lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17077:48"/>nauigare:</hi> let vs ſow our ſeede while it is ſeede time, and ſet forward to ſaile, while the ſea will ſerue. For it may be it wilbe too late to begin our iorney when the ſunne ſetts;
<note place="margin">Numb. 25.</note> to hoyſt vp ſaile, when the tempeſt ariſeth, to ſow our ſeede, when we ſhould reape our corne to repent when we lie a dying, and to do good when we are dead. Remember that Zimry and Gozby were apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed in the very acte of their iniquitie, and ſuddenly were deſtroyed.
<note place="margin">Actes. 5.</note> And A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanias and Saphyra, were taken in the very moment of their ſin, and without repentance periſhed, yea ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine; ſpiritus reprobus repente in morte ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietur á corpore.</hi> The reprobate and ſinfull ſoule ſhall be ſuddenly taken, from the body in the moment of death, and carried with vnſpeakeable feare before the tribunall of the greate iudge of heauen and earth. Then ſhall the ſoule in the remembrance of her ſinnes ſeeke of flye away from them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt but truce &amp; reſpite of one howre to be ſeperated from their ſight and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, but ſhall not obtaine it. For they<pb facs="tcp:17077:49"/>will anſweare <hi>opera tua ſumus, et tec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ibimus,</hi> we are thy ſinnes, &amp; the worke of that hands and heart, and we will goe with thee euen to the iudgement ſeate of God, there to accuſe, and for euer to condemne thee.
<note place="margin">Luke. 16.2</note> Thus happened it vnto the rich man in the Goſpell, who being euen now in pleaſure and delight, and not regarding repentaunce was not long after ſmitten dead, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to hell fire for euer to be burned. This made that holy father Gregorie
<hi>Nazinzin</hi> to ſay.</p>
            <p>One thing I lament and I feare an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the firſt is my ſins, and the ſecond is gods iudgment ſeate, with hell fire.
<note place="margin">Baſill.</note> O therefore ſaith
<hi>Baſill</hi> bewaile euer thy ſinnes, and lament for thy ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.
<note place="margin">Aug.</note> Flie flie thoſe deſtroying tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>vbi nec tortores deſiciunt, nec torti miſere morientur:</hi> where the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are neuer wearie, nor the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhall euer die. Where is death with outextinction, and burning without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. Wherefore while it is to day harden not thy heart but caſt off
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17077:49"/>thy ſinne and remoue thy iniquitie, by true repentance for thy tranſgre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt remedy, and that is to giue a remoue vnto thy ſin. Now followeth the ſecond, which is to caſt thy burthen vpon the Lord, which is to lay it downe in the boſome &amp; lap of God and that muſt be done by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and affiance. Thus did <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 6.</note> Firſt he cryed my ſoule is ſoare troubled, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee prayeth, returne O Lord: which prayer being grounded vpon true faith he ſaith: the Lord hath heared the voyce of my petition, &amp; therfore he triumphs all my enemies ſhall be confounded. Marke the burden which was the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his ſoule, and the remedy, which was prayer and affiance. Wherefore being well practiſed in this diuine art, he ſets vp a ſchoole for al chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſaying: come, and I will teach you. And what (I pray you) is his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod? Firſt decline from euill and then do good, there is the remedy of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the Lordes eares ſhalbe ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your cry &amp; he will deliuer you there<pb facs="tcp:17077:50"/>is the remedy of faith, and prayer; This was <hi>Auguſtines</hi> practiſe;
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.24 Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eah. 14.10.</note> Firſt he cryeth with .S. <hi>Paule</hi> O wretched man that I am, when ſhall my crookedneſſe, be made euen to thy ſtreightneſſe? &amp; then he falleth to confeſſion, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth to be the verie way, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by he may go againe into the way out of the which he hath gone aſtray. Now his confeſſion is that God is truth, and he vanitie, God is puritie but he filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, God is good, but he euill, God is righteous, but he ſinfull, God is life but he dead. Then he falleth vnto prayer, ſaying:
<note place="margin">Aug ſolit. 16,</note> 
               <hi>Audi o Creator, creatura tua ſum iam perij, creatura tua ſum, iam morior.</hi> Hearken then O Creator, I am thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and am now caſt away, I am thy creature, and now do I die: thy work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip (O Lord) I am, deſpiſe not the workes of thy hands, reſpect the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of thy owne hands (I beſeech thee) loe thou haſt written me vpon the palme of they hands: <hi>lege ſcripturam hanc &amp; ſalua me:</hi> read that writing and ſaue me: which prayer being grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on faith, he calleth God his fortitude <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17077:50"/>by whome he is vpholden, his helpe by whome he is aſſiſted, his ſtrength by whome he is ſuſtained, his glorie, in whome he reioyceth, &amp; his life where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he liueth.</p>
            <p>This method Baſilius in his booke <hi>de Peccato</hi> commendeth vnto vs as the eſpeciall remedy for this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſaying; there is one thing that thou muſt ſhun and eſchew, and that is ſinne, inſinuating repentance, and there is one refuge for all thy miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and that is God, intimating faith and true prayer. Let vs therefore take vp the parable of
<hi>Gregorie Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi> and pray after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</p>
            <p>Thou O God haſt had mercie vpon three famous Publicans, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred in thy holy booke:
<note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Mathew</hi> at the cuſtome.
<note place="margin">Luke. 18.</note> The Publican in the Temple.
<note place="margin">Luke. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Zacheus</hi> on the tree: O let me be the fourth and ſaue me. Thou haſt had mercy vpon three, that were ſtrongly bound and couldſt nor ſtirre. The lame of the palſey on the bed, the<pb facs="tcp:17077:51"/>
               <note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> ſicke lying by the poole, and the bound by the ſpirit eightene yeares;
<note place="margin">Marke. 9.</note> O Lord I am bound with the chayne of my ſins, vnlooſe this chaine, let me be the fourth and ſaue me.

<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> Thou haſt had mercy vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on three that were dead, and ſaw no light.
<note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> The Rulers daughter.
<note place="margin">Luke. 7</note> The widdowes ſonne.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 11.</note> And Lazarus whome thou loueſt. O Lord I am dead in my ſinnes, let me bee the fourth and ſaue me, For thy great mercy ſake.</p>
            <p>And nowe giue me coraſiues, that then I may haue comfortatiues. If in this life thou ſendeſt me vanitie, there I ſhall haue immutabilitie. If in this life thou layeſt burdens vpon me, grant that in that life I may enioy eternal eaſe and quietneſſe. And thus much for the third point, which is the remedy for this burden.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the third thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the firſt part, which is the ground whereunto this anker muſt be faſtened: and that is two fold, God, and the promiſe to the prouidence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:17077:51"/>The firſt expreſſed in theſe wordes
<hi>caſt thy burden vpon the Lord.</hi> And the ſecond ſignified by theſe: <hi>He ſhal nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is <hi>gnal Ichouah:</hi> vpon Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah ſhewing vnto vs by this name that God is he of whom all things haue their being, are gouerned, and preſerued For Iehouah is a name of effence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of
<hi>houah,</hi> or <hi>hxiah,</hi> which is a verbe ſubſtantiue, and ſignifieth to be. From whence ariſeth <hi>ehte:</hi> the name of ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peternitie, &amp; ſignifieth which is, which was, and euer ſhall be. Wherefore God calleth himſelf,
<note place="margin">Exod us. 3.14.</note> (and none but himſelf) I am, as who ſhould ſay: I am of my ſelfe, and others of me, and therefore
<hi>caſt vpon me.</hi> I am all ſufficient, hauing no neede of others, but all other things haue neede of me. <hi>Sciebat enim ſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum eſſe, alias creatures a ſe accepiſſe vt eſſent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origin.</note> For he knew well when he ſaid I am: that he onely had being of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp; all the being that the creatures haue, they receiue it from him. Which indeede is no more to be called being (in reſpect of Gods being) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow<pb facs="tcp:17077:52"/>may be ſaid to be, in reſpect of the body, or the ſmoake, in compariſon of the fire. Seeing then God is, and all ſufficient, we note from this word Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah theſe two thinges. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Gods ſelfe exiſtencie, and Gods ſelfe ſufficiencie.</p>
            <p>Firſt Gods ſelfe exiſtencie, whence he is called
<hi>(Alpha)</hi> and <hi>(Omega)</hi> the beginning and the ending which is, which was, and which is to come.
<note place="margin">Apocall. 8.</note> For Attahel: before the mountaines were made, and before the earth, world were formed, euen from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting to euerlaſting, thou art our God (ſaith the kingly Prophet)
<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.2.</note> being the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>created maker of all things yea the very author of life.
<note place="margin">Damacen. Orthodox cap.2.</note> For of him we liue, we moue, and haue our being.
<note place="margin">Acts. 2.15.</note> Ezekias dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, he prolonged at his pleaſure,
<note place="margin">Acts. 17.</note> For he hath power both of life, &amp; death: other Gods cannot ſaue thee, for they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſaue themſelues.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 38.</note> Being like vnto Dagon the God of the Philiſtines,
<note place="margin">Wiſedome 16.13.</note> who fell vpon his face on the ground before the Arke of the Lord, and not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to help himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Barauch. 6.</note> loſt both his head.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17077:52"/>and his hands. But <hi>Iehouah</hi> is he, that did anſwere Elias prayer by fire from heauen.
<note place="margin">Kings. 1.18.</note> For the Lord himſelfe is God, therefore call upon him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is Gods ſelfe ſufficiencie. For God calleth himſelfe <hi>el ſhadday</hi> God all ſufficient, being moſt worthy of that prayſe and commendation, which the Poet aſcribeth vnto nature:
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 17.1.</note> ſaying.
<q>
                  <l>Ipſa ſuis pollens opibus, nihil indiga noſtri.</l>
               </q> He is rich enough of himſelfe and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth none of our riches to helpe him. And thus much he acknowledgeth of himſelfe ſaying. Heare O my people and I will ſpeake: Heare O Iſraell, and I will teſtifie vnto thee.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.7.8.9.</note> For I am God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thy God. I will take no Bullocke out of thy houſe, nor goates out of thy foldes. For all the beaſtes of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt are mine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the beaſtes on a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand mountaines. I know all the fowles on the mountianes, and the wild beaſts of the feild are mine: If I be hungry I will not tell thee. For the world is mine and all that there in is. And thus much the word God importeth vnto<pb facs="tcp:17077:53"/>vs.
<note place="margin">Euripides,</note> For if he be God indeede he neither wants, nor ſtands in neede of any other but our God is almightie.
<note place="margin">Iob. 5.17.</note> He made heauen and earth, and all that is therein And this is the law of reaſon, that <hi>omnis qui aliquid facit, eorum quae facit habeat poteſtatem;</hi> that euery man who makes of effects any thing, ſhould haue power and dominion ouer the workes of his owne hands.
<note place="margin">Caſſiodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus in Pſal. 94.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſhould I ſpende my time in prouing of Gods ſufficiency: ſeeing he is not onely
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: but alſo
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: yea and likewiſe
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for himſelfe, but alſo for others yea and ſufficient for all be they neuer ſo many.
<note place="margin">Zenephon.</note> For of him be all,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: nothing can bee without God:
<note place="margin">Ariſt. de. Mundo.</note> who As
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his booke <hi>ae Mundo</hi> ſaith, that he is as the gouernour in the ſhip: the wagoner in the wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, the Chanter in the Quire, the law in the Cittie, the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in the army; the ſame and much more is God in the world. Now the ſhip cannot long indure without the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17077:53"/>Pilote, nor the Citie without the law, nor the army without the Captaine, nor the world without God. For God is vnto the world, as the Sunne unto the Moone: <hi>quo recedente deficit lumen Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A quinas in Colloſ.</note> But if the Sun pull backe his light from the Mooneſhe muſt likewiſe looſe her light, and if God withdraw his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d from vpholding the world, the world muſt needes decay. And therefore caſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, for he only hath being of him ſelfe, and is ſufficient for himſelfe &amp; thee And thus much for the firſt ground.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the promiſe of Gods prouidence: noted in theſe words: <hi>He ſhall nouriſh thee:</hi> wherefore he may be called
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: of
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: becauſe God by his prouidence, doeth as it were forerunne and prouide nouriſhment for all things.
<note place="margin">Greg. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen de prouid.</note> And good reaſon, For <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt bee
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: he that made all things muſt prouide for all things, otherwiſe there would fall out ſome lacke or want, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the maker, or in the prouider. For if one ſhould make the world, and another keepe, and conſerue it: the one would be weary of working miſdowb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<pb facs="tcp:17077:54"/>the care of the prouider, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther careleſſe in keeping, fearing the goodneſſe of the worker, wherefore
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the generation conſeruation &amp; gouerment of all things are not amiſſe alledged by the Fathers to proceede, and come from one &amp; the ſelfe ſame power.</p>
            <p>The firſt nothing his creating facultie the ſecond, is conſeruing, and the third his ruling an guiding power. And this is acknowledged by the word of God, and practiſed by the creatures. For the eyes of all thinges looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) ſpeaking of the Lord)
<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.15 16.</note> and thou giueſt them their meat in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, thou openeſt thy hands, and filleſt all thinges liuing, of thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.4.</note> This the rauening Lion confeſſeth by his practiſe. For the Lions roaring after their pray, do ſeeke their meat at God. And naturall Philoſophy relating the nature of the creatures doth warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as much vnto vs. For they ripping vp the nature of the crow, do finde in her <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: a certaine vnnaturall affection towards her young ones, who behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17077:54"/>the tallowy couller of her birdes when they are young, falleth into a loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and miſliking of them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for certaine dayes ſhe leaueth and forſaketh them, whome God taking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his cuſtody in meane time ſuſtaines &amp; releiues by worms, that breed in the doung and filth of their neſt, vntill ſuch time as the old ones returne vnto them againe.
<note place="margin">Iob. 39.3.</note> For he prepareth meate for the Rauen, when his birdes cry vnto him wandring for lacke of meate.</p>
            <p>This is further ſhewed by Gods mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſe preſeruation of the Kings Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher a ſea birde. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<note place="margin">Baſil, de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> precat.</note> Who maketh her neſt vpon the water of the ſea, and that in the middeſt of winter, euen then, when the windes are moſt ſtrong, and the water moſt boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous. Yet by Gods prouidence the windes wax quiet, &amp; the waters calme, ſo long as the Halcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſits vpon her eggs and produceth her young ones: yea for ſo long as the young ones haue neede of their damnes nouriſhment and are not fitt to prouide for themſelues: And theſe dayes the ſaylers call the Halcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian<pb facs="tcp:17077:55"/>dayes. Thus God ſheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Father vnto his creatures, being (as the pſalmiſt ſpeaketh) like vnto a father that hath compaſſion vpon his children. And good reaſon that the Lord ſhould be thus vnto vs, if we truſt in him. For do we not ſee the plants giue life, &amp; nouriſhment, vnto the ſpig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and twigges, that ariſe and iſſue of them. The beaſtes cherriſh and now<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh their young, and man bringeth vp his Children that be borne of his loynes.
<note place="margin">Plato.</note> And doe wee thinke that God can bee without naturall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that is the Creator and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, of all fatherly loue in others? yea and is the cauſe of all the good in nature and he himſelfe be without goodneſſe vnto his creature? yes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily,
<hi>cogita de Deo quicquid melius poteſt &amp; de te quicquid deterius, &amp; de illo am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius credere debes, quam cogitare poſſis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernardus. Meditat. 5.</note> Thinke the beſt that thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt of God, and the worſt thou canſt of thy ſelfe, notwithſtanding thou mayſt beleeue much more touching his goodnes, then
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17077:55"/>thou canſt poſſibly thinke our image in For he is
<hi>bonum, ſine quo nihil eſt bonum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſolil. 1.</note> he is goodneſſe it ſelfe without whome nothing is good: yea indeede none is good but one, and that is God himſelfe And therefore caſt thy burden vpon him; for he is thy ſheaphard that will keepe thee ſo that thou ſhall not want: and thy ſhepheard that will ſeeke thee ſo that thou canſt not be loſt.
<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> He is like vnto a eagle that defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds her young ones againſt the heate of the ſunne, and the rigour of the cold.
<note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> Like vnto an hen that keepes her young ones againſt the fury of the vulture:
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> and may be wel compared to the winges of the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,
<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> which are alwaiſe ſpread abroad to receiue thee at thy comming. O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore praiſe the name of the Lord, for he is good, the earth is full of his goodnes.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.</note> Thus doth ſaints giue thanks vnto God <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106 for his goodneſſe.
<note place="margin">Pindarus.</note> But alas and not onely but alſo olde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and frendſhip is now a ſleepe, for men at theſe dayes are too forgetful and not onely old fauour but new like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,<pb facs="tcp:17077:56"/>yea all the graces and louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Lord are put out of mind, and forgotten wherein men are like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iſraelites that forgot God their Sauiour, which had done greeat things in Aegypt, and wonderous thinges in the land of Ham, and fearefull things at the read Sea: yet incontinently they for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gat his workes.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.13.21.</note> Thus are men leade from God, and therefore woe and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction ſhalbe vpon them, (ſaith the Prophet)
<note place="margin">Ier. 2.12.</note> yea, be aſtonied oye heauens, be affraid and vtterly confounded (ſaith the Lord) For my people haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted two euills, they haue forſaken me the fountaine of liuing waters, to dig them pits that will hold no water. For they haue forſaken God the rocke, the foundation and the ſure ground, to caſt vpon the creature, a ſandie vnſteadfaſt &amp; deceitfull grownd. And this grownd is eſpecially of three ſorts, wherevpon men eſpecially caſt their confidence, &amp; faſten their ankers, and they are men, the world, and the deuill.
<note place="margin">Chro. 2.16 12.</note> The firſt grownde whereupon men commonly caſt, is man himſelfe. As ſometimes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17077:56"/>vpon the Phiſician; thus did <hi>Aſa,</hi> who being ſicke and diſeaſed, ſought not to the Lord in his diſeaſe, but to the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: but death ouertooke him for it. Not that phiſicke is to be diſcommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for the Phiſician is honourable, but hee muſt be put in the ſecond or third place. Sometime vpon pollicy, as did <hi>Nero</hi> and
<hi>Abſolon:</hi> the firſt whereof that he might eſtabliſh his kingdome the better to him, and win the hearts of the people, under the pretence of cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie when there was brought a bill vnto him, whereunto hee ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, touching the condemnation &amp; puniſhment of offenders, he would ſay <hi>Vtinam non ſciſſem
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itteras,</hi> I would I could not wright, as though (forſooth) he deſired ſo much the wellfare and life of the people, that wiſhed afterwardes that all Roome were but one head, that he might cut it off at one blow.
<note place="margin">Sam. 2.15.</note> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond that he might with more eaſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the kingdome,
<note place="margin">2.3.5.5.6.</note> hee would get vp earely and ſtand by the entring in of the gate, and euery man that had anie matter, and came to the king for iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<pb facs="tcp:17077:57"/>him did <hi>Abſolon</hi> call vnto him, and ſaid of what cittie art thou? and he anſweared, thy ſeruant is of one of the tribes of Iſraell: then <hi>Abſolon</hi> ſaid vnto him: ſee thy matters are good &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but there is no man deputed of the King to heare thee. <hi>Abſolon</hi> ſaid moreover, O that I were made iudge in the land, that euery man which hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matter or controuerſie might come to me, that I might do him iuſtice. And when any man came neare vnto him, and did him obeyſance, he put forth his hand and tooke him and kiſſed him. And on this manner did <hi>Abſolon</hi> to all Iſraell that came to the King for Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So <hi>Abſolon</hi> ſtale the hearts of the people of Iſraell. See the nature of the pollitician; without a ſaint; within an hypocrite, deceiuer, murderer and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. And yet this is the practiſe of the world by pollicie, hypocriſie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, to aduance, an maintaine their houſe and their eſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Sam. 2.17.</note> but how God liketh the pollician (when pollicy hath not his warrant from him) appeares by the confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Achitophel</hi> whoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17077:57"/>and pollice being refuſed and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, he went and hanged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:</p>
            <p>Thirdly vpon ſtrength, as vpon kings and princes, ſouldiers, holds, muni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and ſuch like.
<note place="margin">Sam. 1.17.17.</note> Thus did <hi>Goliah</hi> truſt in his ſtrength, and therefore deſied the hoſt of Iſraell, but little <hi>Dauid</hi> ouerca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e him with a ſling, and a ſtone. For the battle is the Lords.
<note place="margin">Chro. 2.16.2.</note> Thus did <hi>Aſa</hi> truſt vpon <hi>Benhadas</hi> the King of Aram, but the Lord told him by the Prophet <hi>Haanaus,</hi> that he had done fooliſhly, &amp; therefore henceforth hee ſhould haue warrs. For the eyes of the Lord behold all the earth to ſhew himſelfe ſtrong with them that are of perfect heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.
<note place="margin">Dan. 4.27.25.29.</note> Thus did
<hi>Nabuchadonezer</hi> caſt his confidence vpon the ſtrength of his Babell, ſaying. Is not this great Babell that I haue built for the houſe of my kingdome, by the might of my power, and for the honour of my maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie? But while the word was in his mouth, a voyce came down from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſaying: O King <hi>Nabuchadonezer,</hi> to thee be it ſpoken, thy kingdome is
<pb facs="tcp:17077:58"/>departed from thee, and they ſhall driue thee from men, and thy dwelling ſhall be with the beaſts of the field, they ſhal make thee eate graſſe as the oxen, and ſeuen times ſhall paſſe ouer thee, vntill thou knoweſt, that the moſt highe bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth rule ouer the kingdomes of men, and giueth it vnto whomeſoeuer hee will. And the very ſame houre was this thing fulfilled. Thus did <hi>Dioniſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> that ſaid his kingdome was
<hi>Adaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinis vinculis firmatum.</hi> Strenghtened with chaines of Adamant, and that in deſpite of God, but the blaſphemous wretch found the contrary, when hee was diſpoſſeſſed of it. And Aiax in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phocles truſting vnto his ſtrength, ſaid, <hi>ignauis opus eſſe conſilio diuino, ſe ſine deo vincere poſſe,</hi> it is enough for cowardes to craue ayde and counſell at Gods hands, he was able of himſelfe to get the conqueſt. But he ſpake as a man without a minde, as afterwards it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, when he fought with ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es in ſtead of men. Wherefore for all their brags theſe men muſt know, that there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conqueſt, battle or victory with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17077:58"/>God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.16.</note> and that the king is not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the multitude of an hoſt,
<note place="margin">Iudges. 7.</note> nor the mightie by much ſtrength Gedeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s army conſiſting but of three hundred men ouerthrew a mightie hoſt of the Madianites.
<note place="margin">Chro. 14.9.</note> For the Lord can ſaue as well with a few as with many.
<note place="margin">Sam. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> and his harneſſe bearer, being but two, diſcomfited a mightie armie of the Philiſtines.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.10.</note> For the Lord hath no pleaſure in any mans legges, but in them that feare him.
<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Sicera</hi> had 700 chariots of iron, and a mightie army, yet was ſlaine by 200 men, for they fought from heauen againſt him.
<note place="margin">Aug. deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. 5. cap. 23.</note> The Gothes comming againſt Rome in the reigne of Honorius, were in one day diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>comfited and there King <hi>Radagiſus</hi> with his ſonnes taken captiue, yet not one of the Romans killed, no not ſo much as wounded.
<note place="margin">Ier. 17.5.</note> For curſed is the man, that hopeth in man and maketh fleſh his arme.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.11</note> Becauſe all men are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ares and meare vanitie, being like vnto runing water, yea to a very ſwift ſtream that is here now and ſuddainly in an other place, or like to the falling of
<note place="margin">Epictetus</note>
               <note place="margin">Homer.</note>
               <note place="margin">Sophortes.</note>
               <note place="margin">Pindarus.</note> 
               <pb facs="tcp:17077:59"/>leaues, yea to the ſhadow of ſmoke: nay man is the very dreame of a ſhadow.
<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. 27. ad po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli.</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared by on to houſes of dirt built by litle childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may breake with euery fillip. This made Xerxes to weepe, beholding his great army of 200000 men, becauſe after a few yeares not one of them ſhould remaine, or be aliue. <hi>O ſi poſſemus in tale aſcendere ſpeculum, de quo vniuerſam terram ſub noſtris pedibus cerneremus, iam tibi oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derem totius orbis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uinam.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron: ad Heliodor.</note> O that wee might aſcend to ſuch a hill, from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we might behold all the whole world vnder our feete, then would I quickely ſhew vnto thee, the ruines of the ſame. Then would I ſhew vnto thee nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt nations, wars, impriſome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, tortures, baniſhments, and not only the ruine of Xerxes army, but the death &amp; deſtruction of all the men in the world not long after to come to paſſe.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 40.</note> For all fleſh is graſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flos apparuimus, qui non eramus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi flos ariſcimus qui temporaliter appare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregory</note> We ſeemed to be what wee were not, as a flower we wither which<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17077:59"/>are here but for a time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now may wee thinke ourſelues to be iolly fellowes, but by and by we ſhalbe turned vnto duſt, and then is the peaſant equall with the prince.
<note place="margin">Nazinauz.</note> Therefore let vs in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (enpironed now with enemies) make God alone our ſhield with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.2.</note> yea our rocke and defenſe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> Let vs pray vnto him he is our King, and he muſt heare vs.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.3.</note> For if the woman could anſweare <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperour, when her ſuite was put off with,
<hi>non eſt mihi Otium,</hi> I am not at leaſure: <hi>Ergo imperare noli.</hi>
               <note place="margin">King. 2.6.</note> therefore be no longer King then ſaith ſhe, whereat he turning vnto her, gaue her audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.12</note> How much more will God (that comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vs to pray vnto him) be willing and readie to here our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? <hi>Elizeus</hi> prayed and ſaw the army of God pitched round about him. And <hi>Iacob</hi> had the hoſt of God to meete him for his protection. For the Angell of the Lord ſhall pitch his tentes about thee, and carrie thee in their hands leaſt thou be hurt, if thou wilt put thy truſt in him. And therefore caſt vpon the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:17077:60"/>And thus much for the firſt ground whereupon the moſt part do caſt their anker.
<note place="margin">Pſal, 94.6.</note> The ſecond is the world, where on the couetous, luxurious, idle &amp; ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting man doth put his truſt. For the couetous boaſteth of his riches, &amp; truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in them, ſaying vnto his ſoule, take thy reſt, For thou haſt many goods layd vp.

<note place="margin">Bernard:</note> Theis ſayle <hi>mare rubrum,</hi> the red ſea, and fetch about to the riuer Ganges, which compaſſeth the land of Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>la, where are bred the carbuncle, the Smaragde, and the golden mountaines, whereunto by reaſon of griffens, and dragons and mightie monſters, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt vnpoſſible to attaine.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> Yet man aduentures for it,
<hi>quarit vt acquirat, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirit vt perdat, perdat vt doleat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baſill.</note> He ſeeks by all meanes to get, he gets to looſe, &amp; he leeſeth to vexe and torment himſelf. O yee ſonnes of men how long will ye ſeeke after vanitie? How long will ye hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t after gold, a net to catch our ſoules, the hooke of death and the baite of ſin? How long will ye ſeeke after riches, the cauſe of warres, the diſcord of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that makes kinſmen forget na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17077:60"/>citizens maintaine ſicophantes, and the high way theeues? Who is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lies, the coyner of falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the author of periury? Are they not riches and the deſire of gold? what made <hi>Ahab</hi> to ſlay his ſubiect? <hi>Achan</hi> to ſteale forbidden goods? and Iudas to betray his Maiſter, was it not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of gold and riches? O remember that couetouſnes is carrid vpon a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, the foure wheeles wherof are <hi>puſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanimitas, in humanitas, contemptus dei, &amp; obliuio mortis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Barnard.</note> faint heartedneſſe, inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, contempt of God, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of death. The coach horſſes that draw the chariot are <hi>tenacitas:</hi> and
<hi>rapacitas,</hi> holdfaſt and rauening. The waggoner is deſire of hauing, and the whippes that ſcourdge forwardes theſe horſſes are, deſire to gette, and feare to looſſe. And yet what haſt thou gote by all this paines, but a Cittie of paper, a runnagate ſeruant, a ſword to peirce thy ſoule, and euerlaſting diſtruction (as did <hi>Diues</hi>) that for his riches was carried in to hell. But thou that by euill meanes thus caſteſt after the world, forgetteſt<pb facs="tcp:17077:61"/>that God is the giuer of all riches, who is the giuer of all thinges: in Citie in feild in cattle and corne, and what not. Wherefore leaſt this be added vnto the heape of thy offences, forſake the world and caſt upon the Lord, and he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for thee.</p>
            <p>But heere ſteps in the idle and delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man obiecting for himſelfe, and his eaſe ſaying: What then neede we for to labour if God be the giuer of all things? But this man muſt know, that when the ſcriptures ſpeake (acknowledging to Gods prayſe) that he giueth all things, yet they debarre not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him the means which God appointed. Thus when the pſalmiſt ſpeaketh,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.9.</note> that the faithfull man who truſteth in God, ſhall haue riches and treaſure, he vſeth the word
<hi>Hoon</hi> which properly ſignifith goodes and riches which are gotten by great inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to admoniſh vs, that riches are be ſtowed vpon vs by thoſe means which God hath ordained fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, of which ſort are labor, paines, care, and ſuch like For man is borne to labour. He goeth out vnto his worke and to his labour<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17077:61"/>vntill the euening, and without labour nothing can proſper. Howbeit both labor, thirſt, ſleepe, and all muſt be done according to the Phiſitions rule, name-in a meane. But heere the idle man will take vp Chriſt his ſpeech for his warant ſaying. Take no thought for thy life what to eate, nor for your body what you ſhall put on. The Rauens neither ſow nor reape, yet God feedeth them, and how much is man better then fowles? But we muſt know that Chriſt forbiddeth not heere labour and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes for prouiſion,
<note place="margin">Luke. 12.15.</note> but giueth vs in charge, not to give ouer our ſelues to a coueteous care of this life, nor la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor,
<hi>ſed mens ſuffoca, ta cura, damnatur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſto:</note> not labour but a minde choaked with care is condemned. <hi>Labor eſt exercen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, but ſollicitudo eſt tollenda:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron.</note> labor is to be vſed, but ouer much care to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, For labour is commanded.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> In the ſweate of thy face, thou ſhalt eate thy bread; vntill thou returne vnto the earth. Whereby we finde condemned the idle begger; vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e God hath, afforded parts fitte for labour. The rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <pb facs="tcp:17077:62"/>&amp; the theife, the belly God, and the Fryar, the couſiner, the ſhifter, and all that liue by their wits without calling. For theſe liue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other mens labour, &amp; not vpon the ſweate of their owne browes, <hi>ſolliciti eſſe vetamur, laborare autem iubemur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> For labour <hi>eſt naturae: ſollicitudo eſt culpae,</hi> weare forbidden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to be two carefull, but we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to labor.
<note place="margin">Tho: Aqui.</note> For labour is of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but care of ſinne, yet neither is all care forbidden. For there is a faithfull and a ſinfull care. The firſt laboureth in his calling, <hi>eſcam in manum domini com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit,</hi> but he leaues the iſſue and euent of all his labor, vnto the hands and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, building vpon him by a ſtrong faith. The ſecond laboureth but diſpaires of the iſſue, <hi>quaſi quinemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habet gubernantem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> as though all muſt come by his care and trauell; and there were no God to prouide for him and ſend a bleſſing to his labor.
<note place="margin">Nazenze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, If the Lord giue a bleſſing carking care wil not preuaile: and if God do not giue a bleſſing, all our labour will doe no good. For as the Rabbines could
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17077:62"/>well note God hath foure keys which he will not lend to any other. The key of the graue: the key of dearth an bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renes. The key of raine, and plentie. And the key of foode and nouriſhment: yea except the Lord build the houſe, they la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour but in vaine that build it: and except the Lord keepe the Citie, the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per watcheth but in vaine. It is in vaine for you to riſe earely, and to lie downe late, and eate the bread of ſorrow, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the lord be with you to bleſſe you
<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.1. &amp;. 2.</note> But if God lay to his helping hand, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our lawfull calling and diligent inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour then may we be aſſured all things ſhall proſper, and ſucceed for our good So then, if we will not tempt God wee muſt vſe the meanes, but ſuch meanes as God alloweth of, and hath ordained. Wherefore craft, vſury, Simony, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting of wares, and ſuch like, as meanes by God both forbidden and condemned, are to be eſchewed and auoyded. And here may the poore man that faithfully laboureth in his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling be comforted. For he ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe if God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth<pb facs="tcp:17077:63"/>for the fowles, man is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they.
<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> If he cloatheth the Lillies of the feild, which to day are in your feild, &amp; to morrow caſt into the ouen: how much more will he cloath and feede us, if we will put our truſt in him? This <hi>Dauid</hi> founde by experience, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh others by his example to truſt in God.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.4.6.8.</note> I ſought the Lord (ſaith he) &amp; he hearde me, the poore crieth, and the Lord heareth him: O do but taſt, and ſee how gratious the Lord is, and you ſhall finde that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be greatly bleſſed that putteth his truſt in him. And this Chriſt maketh vs to be moſt ſure of, when he telleth vs that God is our far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For if <hi>pater, vult; If omnipotens poteſt, non eſt ergo timendum quin proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat nobis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> If he be our father, then how can we doubt of his good will vnto vs his children: and if he be omnipotent how can we feare his abilitie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorme his will: wherefore if he be both willing and able, let vs aſſure our ſelues that he, and he alone will aſſuredly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for us, and therefore let us caſt vpon the Lord. And thus much for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17077:63"/>the ſecond falſe ground which is the world.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the third, and that is the Diuell. A ground whereon Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, coniurers, witches, an whoſoever follow any ſuch vnlawfull, and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den craft, do caſt their hope and rely. Men mightely miſlead, and be witched with blockiſh Atheiſme, and vn godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yea with ſottiſh forgetfulneſſe, of their owne eſtate and wellfare.
<note place="margin">Per. 1.5.8.</note> For can a man looke for any benefit, or help at the hands of his mortall enemie and profeſſed foe? yet the Diuell, and his angels are our deadly enemies, ſeeking to deuoure vs, and our profeſſed foes by open proclamation from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> Neither is this all; but God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will turne againſt them.
<note place="margin">Leuitic. 20 6.</note> For If any turne after ſuch as worke with ſpirits, &amp; ſouthſayers, to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o a whoring after them, then will I ſet my face againſt that perſon, and will cut him of from a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong my people.
<note place="margin">Sam. 28.</note> Thus happened it to
<hi>Saule</hi> for leauing God, to ſeeke vnto a witch: he was deſtroyed.
<note place="margin">Exod. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Pharoah</hi> run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardes, but he, and all
<pb facs="tcp:17077:64"/>his army periſhed for it.
<note place="margin">Kings. 2.1.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ahaziah</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſicke sent to inquire of Baalze bub the God of Ekron, touching the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecouery of his diſeaſe, but the angell of the Lord ſaid vnto Eliah. Ariſe, and go vp to meete the meſſingers, and ſay vnto them: Is not there a God in Iſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell? wherefore thus ſaith the Lord: Thou ſhalt not come downe from the bed, on which thou art gone vp, but ſhalt die the death, <hi>Domitian</hi> forſooth muſt needes hane his wizards to tell him of his fortune; But preſently thereupon he grew ſuſpitious of all his people, that he cauſed the wall of his gallery to be beſette with the ſtone Phengiles, which is a verie bright and ſhining ſtone, that by that meanes hee might ſee, and behold, what was done behind him.
<note place="margin">Suetonius. cap. 14.15.</note> For theſe fortune tellers, and caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of natiuties either they tel vs
<hi>aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> or <hi>proſpera:</hi> ſome good and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie which ſhall happen vnto vs, or elſe ſome ill and aduerſitie, that ſhall betide vs. If they tell vnto vs ſome happy thing to come and do deceiue vs, they make vs vnhappie by expecting that which <pb facs="tcp:17077:64"/>ſhall neuer be fulfilled. And if they tell vnto vs aduerſe, and euill thinges to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide vs, and lie vnto vs, yet they make vs miſerable by fearing that which ſhal not be effected, Howbeit, if they learn this knowledge of the Diuell, can wee thinke that he will tell vs any good that wiſheth nothing but our hurt? or if it be elſe where to be found, were
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t lawfull? would God then forbid it to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Deutrie. 18.10.11 12.</note> Let none be found amongſt you that vſeth witchcraft, or a regarder of times, or a marker of the flying of fowles, or a Sorcerer, or a charmer, or that counſelleth with ſpirits, or a ſouth-ſayer, or that asketh counſel at the dead For all that doe ſuch things are an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination vnto the Lord.
<note place="margin">Iudges. 9.</note> As for the Diuell he is an euill ſpirit, the ſpirit of hatered, a lying ſpirit, and the father of lyes, himſelfe like lightening was throwen downe from heauen. And what ſtay then can they hope for or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that put their truſt in him?
<note place="margin">Kings. 1.22</note> But if thou haſt ſayd with <hi>Dauid,</hi> the Lord is my hope, and my fortreſſe, hee is my God, in him will I truſt.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 13.</note> Then ſhalt <pb facs="tcp:17077:65"/>thou be deliuered from the ſnare of the hunter, and from the noy ſome peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from the feare of the night and the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that flieth by day:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.</note> Thou ſhale walke vpon the Lion; and the Adder, the young Lyon, or the Dragon ſhalt thou treade vnder thy feete. For God will give his Angels charge ouer thee, to keepe thee in all thy wayes: As for the Diuell, what power and abilitie hath he to preuaile againſt thee, vnleſſe God giue him leaue,
<note place="margin">Gregorius</note> 
               <hi>Qui etsam in porcos tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire non potu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, niſi permiſſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 8.</note> which could not enter into the heard of ſwine vntill he had receiued leaue and licence from Chriſt our Sauiour.
<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> Nor preuaile againſt Iob, no further then the Lord ſawe it, conuenient, for Iobs triall, &amp; the Lords glorie. Wherefore defie Sathan, and abandon all vſers of wicked craftes, &amp; ſay with <hi>Auguſtine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Vna confidentia, vna
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irma promiſſio Deus miſerecordia tua.</hi> This is one only confidence, and firme promiſe, and that is thy mercy O God. <hi>Si inſurgant aduerſiis me praelia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernardus.</note> Though warres and troubles riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me. Though the world rage, and<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17077:65"/>the Diuell fret. Though the fleſh luſt againſt the ſpirit, yet <hi>in te domine ſperae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo:</hi> I will truſt in thee: In thee O Lord alone, my God, and my redeemer.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.</note> And with <hi>Dauid</hi> though my aduerſaries be increaſed, and ſay vnto my ſoule, there is no helpe for him in his God, yet will I not be affraid for ten thouſand. For thou O God art my buckler, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation belongeth onely vnto thee. O Chriſt my king thou art my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, my ſtrength my riches, my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, yea thou art all thinges what tounge can ſpeake, or heart can wiſh heere heere is the ſure ground whereon, to caſt our anker, other grounds will but deceiue
<note place="margin">Gregory.</note> vs. <hi>Quid coelo ſecurius, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſo iucundus? Angeli tumen de caelo, de pariaiſo homines c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciderunt.</hi> What is more ſecure then heauen, or more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant then paridiſe? yet the Angels fell from heauen and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e loſt paradiſe: why then wilt thou caſt vpon man, which is ſo fraile, the world which is ſo vaine, and the Diuell which is ſo deceitfull.
<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Proijce te in illum qui ſemper ſtat:</hi> O no but caſt thy ſelfe only vpon him, which is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:17077:66"/>fraile, or vaine, ſubtle, nor deceitfull but firme, conſtant and permanent, wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling to receiue thee, and able for to help thee, euen the Lord thy God and he will nouriſh thee: and thus much for the firſt part of this text, which is the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mans laying at anker in the ſea of this world contained in theſe wordes, caſt thy burden vpon the Lord and he will nouriſh thee.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the ſecond and the third partes which for the time is paſt, I will contract and finiſh in a word.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part is the arriuing of the godly man in the hauen of happpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Contained in theſe words, He will not ſuffer the righteous to fall for euer, inſinuating vnto vs, that the godly man ſhall be toſſed in this world with the waues of aflictions, and the windes of perſecutions, but for all this he ſhall be deliuered from drowning, and at the laſt arriue in the bleſſed ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of happineſſe, where in we are to conſider theſe two things. Firſt the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of afflictions, and ſecondly the<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17077:66"/>aſſurance of his arriuing in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>The firſt inſinuated from the compariſon of his ſayling &amp; the ſecond aſſured from the promiſe. Who will not ſuffer him to fall for euer; for the firſt.</p>
            <p>Mans life is compared vnto a ſhippe ſayling on the ſea, and therfore he muſt looke for waues and windes to toſſe &amp; aſſault him. To a warrefare: the chriſtian man is the ſouldier, and he muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect weapons, and men, and all ſtore of warlike ſtrategemes to oppreſſe him.
<note place="margin">Timothie. 2.2.3.</note> Thus is
<hi>Timothie</hi> called the ſouldier of Chriſt, and therefore perſwaded by the Apoſtle to arme himſelfe to ſuffer affliction as a good ſouldier. The Chtiſtian man is compared to a veſſell, afflictions are the tooles, &amp; the veſſell muſt looke to be cut and ſquared fitte fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the vſe of that houſe, for which it is prouided. The Chriſtian man is compared vnto a ſcholler, the world is the ſchoolehouſe, afflictions are the rod and the ſcholler muſt looke nowe and then to taſt of the rodde, and vnder goe<pb facs="tcp:17077:67"/>correction.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 66:10.</note> The Chriſtian man is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto gould, the world is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e, afflictions are the fire, and the gould and mettall muſt looke to bee tried in the fire, that it may be purified. The Chriſtian is compared to a runner and tryer of maſteries, and the wreſtler muſt looke for foiles and for falles.
<note place="margin">Cor. 1.9.24.</note> The Chriſtian is compared to come and he muſt looke to be ſifted and threſhed with the flayle of afflictions. The chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man is compared vnto the grape, that muſt be preſſed, ſtrayned and ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with tribulation. Thus God dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with his children as a father with the ſonne, whome he moſt loueth:
<note place="margin">Luke. 15.</note> as a Phiſitian with the patient whome he moſt affecteth, ſpecified by the louing father vnto the prodigall ſon, by Chriſt vnto the theife vpon the croſſe.
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> This was the way for all the god vnto walke into heauen, as appeareth by the patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, the Prophets the Apoſtles, Chriſt and his ſaints wherfore we muſt accept of afflictions, as the Lords moſt father<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly corrections, firſt becauſe God is the ſender of them, and being our father he <pb n="49" facs="tcp:17077:67"/>will ſend nothing vnto his children, but that which ſhall be for their good and profit.

<note place="margin">Luke. 15.</note> How mercifull was hee vnto the wounded man that fell among theiues,
<note place="margin">Math. 9.</note> How carefull was hee of the ſheepe that was loſt in the wilderneſſe?
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> and how pittiful ouer the diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſed, that were ſicke, blind, doumb, and deafe, for vnto whome faith God ſhall I haue reſpect, but vnto him that is miſerable, poore, brought low, troubled in ſpirite, and ſtandeth in awe of my words.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 66.2.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly becauſe God that ſendes them is almightie, and able to deliuer vs: Our father will not ſuffer vs to be tempted aboue our ſtrength.
<note place="margin">Cor. 1.10.</note> Thirdly becauſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are ſhort, yet a little and hee comes. Though mourning be at euen yet ioy cometh in the morning. Thus was <hi>Ioſeph</hi> now a priſoner, by and by a Prince.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.5.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> erewhile a baniſht man, and deſpiſed, by and by a King &amp; much reſpected;
<hi>Iob</hi> a man euen now afflicted and contemned; by and by againe in much proſperitie and of all regarded. Fourthly becauſe we are ſicke, God is the Phyſitian, affliction the phyſicke, &amp;<pb facs="tcp:17077:68"/>we will ſuffer the phiſician to giue vs bitter potions, and the ſurgeon to cutte and to launce our bodies. And why not much more God, who though hee kill yet will make aliue, and though hee wound, yet will make vs whole: In a word becauſe afflictions bring vs to know God and our ſelues, to awake vs from ſin, and conforme vs to the image of Chriſt his ſonne, becauſe in trouble betimes ſhall they ariſe vnto mee ſaith the Lord, and while wee are puniſhed, we are corrected of the Lord, that wee ſhould not be condemned in the world Let vs cry with <hi>Auſtine, hic ſeca, hic v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ne pere am in eternum,</hi> here cut, here launce, here box, here burne leaſt I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with Diues and the reſt of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the fire of hell which ſhall neuer haue an end,
<note place="margin">Actes. 3.</note> yea let vs reioyce in aflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as did the Apoſtles, let vs receiue them with thankes, ſeeing we ſuffer no more for our ſinnes, then Chriſt ſot vs, which had no ſinne.
<note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note> And ſeeing the deſciple is not aboue his maſter but by this way Chriſt our maſter entred into his glorie: let vs humble our ſelves in<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17077:68"/>afffictions for hee that will followe Chriſt, muſt deny him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elfe:
<note place="margin">Luke 24.</note> And afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are Gods cogniſcance to ſhew vs who is our Lord and maiſter.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 33.</note> Let vs repent vs of our ſinne, for God is verie ready to forgiue otherwiſe the Lord will viſit ſinnes with ſcourges, And let vs continually call vpon the Lord, for ſo he commandeth ſaying: call vpon me in time of trouble, and I will deliuer thee,
<note place="margin">Kinges. 2.</note> Thus did <hi>Hezekias</hi> in his ſickenes
<note place="margin">Act. 12.20.</note> and <hi>Peter</hi> in the Priſon, and the one was healed, and the other deliuered; the paines of hell (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>)
<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> came about me, and the ſnare of death ouertooke me, but in my trouble I called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord, and he heard me, for whoſoeuer calleth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of the Lord ſhall be preſerued. And thus much for the firſt point which is the neceſſitie of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> Now followeth the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d which is the certaintie of deliuerance, and arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the hauen of happineſſe noted out of theſe words. He will not ſuffer the righteous to fall for euer. This is warranted from theſe arguments. Firſt from the fore knowledge of God, who<pb facs="tcp:17077:69"/>ſeeth all thinges before they come to paſſe, and therefore ſeeth the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of his people, as he beheld the Iſralites, afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; will deliuer the godly now as he deliuered his people then.
<note place="margin">Exod. 3.78</note> For I haue ſurely ſeene the trouble of my people (ſaith God) which are in Aegipt and haue heard their cry, and therefore am come downe to deliuer them, and to bring them into a land that floweth with milke and hony. See, they ſhall be deliuered becauſe God foreſeeth their calamities, neither is his ſight more dim or his loue leſſe now to them that feare him. All thinges are naked and open in his eyes, he behouldeth the endes of the world, and ſeeth all that is vnder heauen.
<note place="margin">Heb. 4.13.</note> He ſeeth all thinges, hee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all thinges and rewardeth all thinges.
<note place="margin">Orpheus:</note>
            </p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly from Gods goodneſſe and loue that is vnchangeable towardes his ſervantes,
<note place="margin">Luke. 10.28</note> for God hath written their names in heauen, and hath them in his booke of accounts.
<note place="margin">Luke 15.50</note> He will not loſe the loſt ſheepe that is gone aſtray. They are in Corporated into his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17077:69"/>Cittie, and he knowes them by their names.</p>
            <p>Thirdly from his promiſe, who hath promiſed when they crie vnto him, he will deliuer them: the certaintie hereof dependeth vpon his truth, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye, and vpon his omnipotency which cannot faile.</p>
            <p>Fourthly from his iuſtice which will giue to euery one according to their deſertes and therefore if not in this world yet in the world to come he will giue a worthy bleſſinge vnto the godly.</p>
            <p>Fifthly from his mercie, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his ſonne to ſhine both on good and badde, and will not alwaiſe forget his mercie vnto his ſeruants that call vpon him. This is Chriſt his banner, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the ſeruants of Chriſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially do march. This is their tower wherunto they fly in all their aſſaultes, yea this was that which brake hell gates to let out the ſeruants of God, and it will open the dores of heauen to let in all thoſe, that with true faith caſt vpon Chriſt their true ground &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:17077:70"/>Laſtly this is warranted from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of all the Saints in holy writte, whome God preſerued in the time of trouble. Noah was ſaued when the world was drowned, for he truſted in God. Lot was preſerved when Sodom was burned for he ſerued God. The Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites were deliuered, when Pharaoh periſhed becauſe they where the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord what ſhould I rippe vp a volumne of examples? when Dines periſhed in hell for his wickedneſſe, <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> was carried into heauen for his godlineſſe, a kingdome, a throane, and paradiſe of bliſſe, not like earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes full of troubles (as was <hi>Dauids</hi>) nor momentary as was <hi>Salomons,</hi> but a kingdome more pure then the ſunne which nothing can corrupt, more rich then pretious ſtone which nothing can valu; a kingdome which neithr eye hath ſeene; nor the glory thereof can any toung relate. What ſouldier would not indure any hard ſhippe for his kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e what wreſtler would nor ſuffer any ſoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les for his wager? What runner any
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17077:70"/>labour for this priſe? what priſoner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fetters for this libertie? what glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any abſtience? what Diues any pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? what
<hi>Abraham</hi> any pilgrimage? what <hi>Dauid</hi> any baniſhment? and what Saint all calamitie, and affliction for this paradiſe? only caſt and truſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and he will prouide it for thee: for he will not ſuffer the righteous to fall for euer. But the vngodly ſhall be throwen into the pitt of corruption. And this is the laſt part of this text: which containeth in it the ſhipwrack of the wicked man: who all be it he ſaile top and top gallant in the ſea of this world, and flouriſh for a while, in the vanitie of the ſame, yet ſhall the waues of an euill conſcience toſſe him, and the winds of Gods judgments vtterly ouer throw him.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quid Craſſos, &amp; Pompeios euertit?</l>
               <l>Summus nempe locus nulla non arte petitus.</l>
               <l>Magnaque numinibus vota exaudita malignis.<note place="margin">Satyr.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſtocke of Craſſus, and the houſe of Pompey flouriſhed in Rome for a<pb facs="tcp:17077:71"/>ſpace, but being erected and ſette vp by ill meanes, &amp; ſubtiltie: was ouerthrown, and came to nothing. This the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture abundantly proueth vnto vs. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times telling vs of the proſperitie of the wicked, and ſometime ſhewing vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the deſtruction of the ſinner. Thus when Iob had declared vnto us, the flou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſhing eſtate of the wicked, vpon the necke thereof he inferreth the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fall of the vngodly. Now he ſaith:
<note place="margin">Iob. 21.71.</note> they liue, wax old, and grow in wealth their houſes are peaceable, and their bul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locke falleth not, they ſend forth childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and reioyce in the ſound of the harpe, and Organes, they ſpend their dayes in wealth, and the rod of God is not vpon them, yet he concludeth; Let the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the wicked be farre from me; for their candle ſhall be put out, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction ſhall come vpon them; they ſhall be as ſtubble before the winde, &amp; as chaffe that the ſtorme carrieth away, yea God will lay vp ſorrow for him, &amp; when he rewardeth him, he ſhall know it.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> So when Dauid had well nie ſlipt, beholding the proſperity of the wicked<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17077:71"/>yet entering into the ſanctuarie of God he vnderſtood the ſlippery ende of the vngodly: who are ſuddenly deſtroyed as a dreame when one waketh.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.6.</note> For the way of the ſinner ſhall periſh <hi>Geminae ſub terra viae ad manes ſunt, Vna eſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum, ſed malorum eſt altera. Te nullus error habeat, eſt ius inferis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.18</note> There bee two waies: the one leadeth to heauen, the other to hell, the one is for the good the other for the bad, and we may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſured that God is iuſt, who will reward them both according to their workes. The firſt ſhall proſper, for the Lord will bleſſe them, but the ſecond ſhall periſh for the face of the Lord is againſt them that do euil, to cut off their reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance from the earth.
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſayled in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie for a while, but at the laſt he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſhipwracke, and was drowned.
<note place="margin">Eſter. 9.</note> Haman ſayled a loft for a while, but at the laſt, fell into his owne pit, and was hanged: Antiochus, proſpered for a while, but at the laſt was ſlaine by Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon, and periſhed. Thus ſhall the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors be deſtroyed, &amp; the ende of the wicked ſhall be cut off. What ſhould <pb facs="tcp:17077:72"/>I heere recken vp the temporary flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>Herod, Nero, Domitian, Traian, Hadrian, Valerian, Aurelian, Diocleſian, Maximinus, Maximianus,</hi> and infinite others? Were not ſome of them deuou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red with wormes, others ſpat out their lunges: ſome killed themſelues, others were murdered by their ſeruants: ſome died of dropſie; others of an apoplexie ſome were taken captiue by the foe, &amp; others deſtroyed by the enimie?
<note place="margin">Kings. 1.11.</note> For God will rayſe vp aduerſaries to <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> for his ſinnes, and muſter all the hoſt of heauen againſt the wicked for their offences.
<note place="margin">Ierimiah. 5.6.</note> A Lyon out of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſhall ſley them a wolphe out of the wilderneſſe ſhall deſtroy them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard ſhall watch ouer their Cittie,
<note place="margin">Actes. 1.18.</note> and euery one that goeth out ſhall be torne in peeces, becauſe of their trangreſſions,
<hi>Iudas</hi> came to perdition by the halter, <hi>Lubian</hi> was deuoured with dogges;
<note place="margin">Actes. 13.</note> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limas</hi> was ſtrucken blind: <hi>Manes</hi> was flead aliue. <hi>Arrius</hi> died of a flux. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius</hi> was ſwallowed vp of the earth, <hi>Benedict</hi> the 9. was ſtrangled by Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and <hi>Zoroaſtes</hi> burned by the Diuell.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17077:72"/>The blaſphemer was ſtoned: and the child that learned betimes to ſweare was poſſeſſed of the diuell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the man that gather<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſtickes on the ſaboth was ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
<note place="margin">Leuit. 24.</note> and <hi>Nicanor</hi> that regarded not the ſabboth was deſtroyed,<note place="margin">Greg. lib. 4. Dial. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Abſolon</hi> was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the haire: and the poſteritie of diſobedient <hi>Cham</hi> was aboliſhed:
<note place="margin">Numb. 15.</note> verily the vngodly may make a ſhew for a while, but they are ſet in ſlippery places,
<note place="margin">Sam. 2.16.</note> Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they ſhall be conſumed.
<note place="margin">Deutri. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Cain</hi> muſt be a runnagate for his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> and <hi>Sodom</hi> burned for vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Achan</hi> was ſtoned for taking a forbidden garment; <hi>Leo, Corponimus</hi> was ſmitten from heauen for ſacriledge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Amaſiaz</hi> muſt die in a polluted lande for falſe witneſſe: <hi>Darius Princes</hi> weare into the Lions den for accuſing <hi>Daniell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Daniell.</note> Thus will the Lord raine vpon the wicked, ſnares fire and brimſtone.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.</note> His hand ſhall finde out all his enemies, and his right hand them that hate him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea the Lord ſhall diſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his wrath and the fire ſhall deuour them.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 21.9</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs be wiſe like the children of this generation, and learne one leſſon <pb facs="tcp:17077:73"/>from the men of Tire, and Sidon, and that is, as they that feared the anger of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rod</hi> the Prince, came to <hi>Blaſtus</hi> the chamberlaine to deſire peace:
<note place="margin">Acts. 12.</note> ſo wee fearing the anger of God the Father, let vs go vnto Chriſt the ſonne, To make atonement for vs; The way muſt be: Firſt by prayer to labour for faith. Secondly by faith to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ttaine repentance. And Thirdly by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to bring forth a new life, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking old <hi>Adam</hi> the man of ſinne, and putting one the newe Chriſt the man of righteouſneſſe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> For then God ſhall bee our father by adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and bleſſed is the people, whoſe God is the Lord: euen the people that hee hath choſen for his inheritance.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.</note> And then though Father, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forſake thee, afflictions and all the world do bande againſt thee yet will the Lord gather thee vp, and with his mightie arme deliuer thee. And therefore caſt (with <hi>Dauid</hi>) vpon the Lord and hee will nouriſh thee. For he will not ſee the righteous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for euer, but the wicked ſhall <pb n="54" facs="tcp:17077:73"/>be throwen into the pit of deſtruction. Whereby thou maiſt know howe to withſtand the aſſaults of Sathan, who taking aduantage vpon thy homebred Atheiſme, ſtirreth vp thy impatient nature to wage warre againſt thy Creature, and ſay with the wicked in Malachie.
<note place="margin">Malach. 3.14.</note> It is in vaine to ſerue God, for they that worke wickednes are exalted: as who ſhould ſay. To ſerue God is neither good for God nor profitable for man. Firſt it is not good for God, for if thou beeſt righteous, what giueſt thou vnto him, Or what receiueth he at thy hand?
<note place="margin">Iob. 35.7.</note> Secondly it is not beneficiall vnto man, for then it ſhould be in one of theſe reſpects, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that God would bleſſe vs for our ſeruice, or not puniſh vs for our ſinnes: but neither are the good men rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for there well doing, nor the bad puniſhed for there wicked working, &amp; therefore it is in vaine to ſerue God: ye on the contrary it is good to be bad and beſt to be the worſt. For are not the humble debaſed, and the proud exalted the wicked man rich and the good man<pb facs="tcp:17077:74"/>poore? doth not oppreſſion, and iniury deceite and coſinage, diſing &amp; ſwearing bring in welth and iolitie, but true dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling makes wo and pouertie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Criminibus debent hortos pretoria meſas,</hi> was not
<hi>Nabuchadonaſar</hi> mightie, yet proud, <hi>Pompie</hi> great, O yet ſacrelegious, <hi>Rapſakie</hi> rich yet a blaſphemer;
<hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> a Monarch, yet ful of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aude aliquidbreuibus gyaris, et carcexe di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſiuis eſſe aliquis; victus laudatur et alget</hi>
               <note place="margin">Malac. 8.2.17.</note> verily he that wold be rich let him be co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous, &amp; he it would be pore let him bee righteous:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.11.13.</note> he it would be great let him be vitious, &amp; he that would be little &amp; of no eſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, let him be virtuous.
<note place="margin">Prou. 5.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For God either delights in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do euil: or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds not our actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: or els hideth away his face &amp; wil not regard;
<note place="margin">Orpheus.</note> al which thou haſt hard euen now anſweared by prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, &amp; proued falſe by wofull experience for God is no idle ſpectator of our actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nor vaine beholder of our works: he wil be fauourable vnto the good, &amp; moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere againſt the bad The waiſe of man are before the eies of the Lord, &amp; he po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dereth all his paths, he beholds al things<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17077:74"/>hears all things &amp; rewards all according to there workes. If thou doeſt wel (ſaith God vnto
<hi>Caine</hi>)
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 4.7.</note> ſhalt thou not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted? &amp; if thou doeſt not well ſin li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at thy dore: and ſaith the heathen man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si genus humanum et mortalia temitis a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ma, at ſperate deos memores fandi at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vira. Acnad. 6.</note> Albeit mortal man is not able to o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ffend thee, nor his weake arme ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand thee, yet the immortal God that keeps a regiſter of our wayes will one day ſette a due deſert vpon our works.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt ſay this puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which God reſerues for an other day is very late: And yet thou muſt know when it ſhall come it will be two bitter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lento garduira deidrocedit, ſed tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> penae grauetate ſupplicij compenſat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Valer. Maxi.</note> God is ſlow indeede vnto anger, and very loth to come vnto reuenge, but when he comes he will recompence his ſlacknes with the greatnes of his puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhments. Thus he delt with the olde world, with Sodom, with the Iewes, day by day, yeare by yeare, age after age ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting<pb facs="tcp:17077:75"/>there repentance, being called more properly
<hi>pater miſerordiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> then <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciorum</hi> the father of mercies, then of iudgments, becauſe the firſt proceedes from himſelfe the ſecond from our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Howbeit thou wilt ſay againe: if God did ſo miſlike ſin or were able to puniſh it he would ſhew ſome token of his power and iuſtice in this life. True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo he doth remember the fall of the Angels, the baniſhment of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the confuſion of Babell: the drowning of the old world, the burning of Sodom: the ouerthrow of <hi>Pharaoh: Saule: Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon: Herod: Iudas:</hi> the ſword, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, the plague inſtruments of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and iuſtice. And if thou wilt learne to diſtinguſh of Gods puniſhmentes, which are two fold, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſecret beſids his open puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon thou ſhalt ſinde his ſecret puniſhments to be continual, namely the ſting of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience which like a neuer wearied furie will purſue the night &amp; day vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 30.</note> The heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could call a guilty co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience <hi>occultum flagellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei Gods hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17077:75"/>
               <hi>whip: Caine</hi> felt the ſinart thereof: and thou canſt not auoyd it.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding thou ſeeſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked flowriſh in this world: which ſtil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth thy infidility &amp; diffide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; ô let it not do ſo, for they haue their portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life:
<note place="margin">Luk. 16.15</note> thus did <hi>Diues</hi> receiue in this world profit, &amp; pleaſure, but <hi>Lazarus</hi> penury &amp; paine: but now is <hi>Lazarus</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted &amp; <hi>Dines</hi> tormented.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.</note> Beſids this there proſperitie is but momentary:
<note place="margin">Iob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> as a dreame, as the ice: as the cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e before the winde; verily vanitie of vanities all is but vanitie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared by the Pſalmiſt to the graſſe, to the hearb: to the fat of the lambes, to the ſmoake, to a clowde that vaniſheth away in a moment, whereas the godly ſhall poſſeſſe the land, for the Lord vpholdeth them:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> the godly ſhall be preſerued for euer, for the Lord is there ſtrength &amp; there ſaluation, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there ende ſhall be peace for euer more.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.16.</note> O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye that feare the Lord har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto his precept publiſhed by the prophet Eſay ſaying, ceaſe to do euill, learne to do well; &amp; giue eare vnto his promiſe proclamed by the prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17077:76"/>ſaying, flye from euill &amp; doe good and dwell for euer, For euer:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.27</note> how can that be, ſeeing our ſelues momentarie our abiding temporary, and our dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling tranſitory.
<note place="margin">Aug. 36.</note> But, <hi>alia terra erit, vbi inhabitabimus in ſecalu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeculi:</hi> there ſhall be an other land, and kingdom wherein we ſhall abide for euermore: an heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kingdome: an eternall kingdome: a moſt bleſſed kingdome:
<note place="margin">Mathe. 25.</note>a Paradiſe: a place of pleaſure:
<note place="margin">Tim. 2.4.</note> a building of God, an houſe that is eternall in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.
<note place="margin">Luke. 14.</note> To which place hee bring vs that hath ſo deerely bought it for vs,
<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> Ieſus Chriſt the righteous.</p>
            <p>Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17077:76"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
